[Host] AI agents 出现之后，Ruby on Rails 的创造者是怎么改变我们如今构建软件的方式的？David Heinemeyer Hanson，大家通常叫他 DHH，是 Ruby on Rails 和 Omachi 的创始人，也是 37 Signals 的联合创始人。
How has the creator of Ruby on Rails changed how we build software now with AI agents? David Heinemeyer Hanson often approaches DHH, creator of Ruby on Rails, Omachi, and is the co-founder of 37 Signals.
[Host] 六个月前，他还在 LexReason 的播客里猛批 AI 编程工具的能力。结果到了寒假那几周里，他来了个 180 度大转弯，几乎所有事情都开始 AI 优先了。
He bashed capabilities of AI coding tools on LexReason's podcast six months ago. Then, over the course of a few weeks over the winter break, he did a 180 turn and went AI first on everything.
[Host] 今天这期对话里，我们会聊 David 和他在 37signals 的团队现在是怎么做软件的，以及 AI 工具如何让他们比以往任何时候都更有野心。
In today's conversation we cover how David and his team at 37signals builds software today and how AI tools are making them more ambitious than ever before.
[Host] 我们还会聊，为什么 Ruby on Rails 和 Linux 可能会比今天更受欢迎，因为它们都非常适合和 AI agents 一起工作。
Why Ruby on Rails and Linux could become even more popular than they are today as they are both well suited working with AI agents.
[Host] 为什么审美和优美的软件变得更重要了，以及为什么那些大胆、有辨识度、又真正重视手艺的设计师和工程师，可能会变得更抢手。还有很多别的话题。
Why taste and beautiful software are becoming more important and why bold standout designers and engineers who care about the craft could become more in demand. and many more.
[Host] 如果你想知道科技行业里最资深的构建者之一，怎么看 AI 工具的实际价值，以及这些工具会怎样影响那些真正重视手艺的软件工程师，那这期节目就是给你的。
If you're interested in what one of the most experienced builders in the tech industry thinks about the practical utility of AI tools and how these tools could impact software engineers who care about the craft, then this episode is for you.
[Host] 本期节目由 Statsig 呈现，它是一个集 flags、分析、实验等功能于一体的统一平台。想进一步了解他们，以及我们本季的另外两家赞助商 Sonar 和 WorkOS，可以查看节目备注。David，很高兴请到你。
This episode is presented by Statsig, the unified platform for flags, analytics experiments, and more. Check out the show notes to learn more about them and our other season sponsor, Sonar and WorkOS. David, it's awesome to have you here.
[Guest] 谢谢邀请我来。其实应该说，谢谢你过来才对。你现在在 Copenhagen。那是我这阵子最想待的城市。那真是一座美丽的城市，优点特别多。
Thanks for having me. Thanks for coming, I should actually say. You're in Copenhagen. That's my city of choice at the moment. It's a beautiful city. It's got so much going for it.
[Host] 那你最近都在忙些什么？
And so what have you been up to?
[Guest] 我一直都在做东西。过去整整三十来年，我都在互联网上不停地做各种东西。我大概是 94 年第一次接触到互联网，从那之后基本就没停过。
I'm always building stuff. I have been building stuff for a good damn three decades now on the internet. I got started back in 94, I think it was, when I first got exposed to it and basically just never stopped.
[Guest] 过去这六个月里，我做了不少东西。其中一个是新的 Linux 发行版，叫 Umachi。我大概是两年多前转到 Linux 的。最开始先用了段时间 Ubuntu，
And in the past six months, I've been building a variety of things. One of them is a new Linux distribution called Umachi. I switched to Linux about a little over two years ago, I think now. First spent some time on Ubuntu,
[Guest] 玩得挺开心，后来又意识到，其实我想从零开始做一套自己的系统，基于 Arch 和 Hyperland 来构建。所以我在 Machi 上投入了很多时间，它最初是我在参加勒芒 24 小时耐力赛间隙做的一个暑期项目。
having fun with that and then realizing I actually wanted to make my own system from scratch, building it on top of Arch and Hyperland. So put a lot of time into Machi, got started as a summer project in between racing at the 24 Hours of Le Mans.
[Guest] 那一周其实有很多空档时间，所以我就开始动手折腾，之后它很快就发展起来了。
There's a lot of downtime in that week. So I just started hacking on it and it really took off very quickly thereafter.
[Guest] 这一路真的很受鼓舞。即便是在 Linux 发行版这么拥挤的市场里，外面大概已经有 7000 种不同的发行版了，
It's been a truly inspiring ride to see that even in a market as crowded as Linux distributions, there's about 7,000 different distributions out there,
[Guest] 有些历史非常悠久，很多在某种程度上甚至连气质都挺相似的。但依然有新东西的空间，这也很好地提醒了我一点。
some of them with long pedigrees and many of them even based on sort of kind of similar vibes to some extent. There's room for something new and it's a great reminder that.
[Guest] 这世界上所有点子可能都已经有人做过了，但那也没关系，因为你的版本还没有。我把自己的那一套放进了 Linux 里，做出了 Machi。
All the ideas in the world may be taken and doesn't matter because your spin on it isn't. And I put my spin on Linux, Buildamachi,
[Guest] 我给自己打造过一套堪称完美的计算机系统，然后我发现了一件和我每次做出真正特别对自己胃口的东西时一模一样的事。
built the perfect computer system for me and saw exactly the same thing I've ever seen whenever I build something that really just hits the spot for me personally.
[Guest] 世界上还有成千上万的人和我一样，或者至少口味足够接近，所以他们也会从这些东西里获得同样的满足和快乐。不管是 Ruby on Rails、Kamal、离开云，还是这些事情里的任何一个，都是同一种症状。
There are thousands of others just like me or close enough to what I like that they find the same pleasure and joy in it, whether it was Ruby on Rails, Kamal getting out of the cloud, any of these things. It's the same syndrome.
[Host] 对，做 Rails 的时候，你其实就是在解决自己的痛点，你只是先做自己的组件，然后把它们开源了。事情一开始就是这样吗？
Yeah, with Rails, you were literally scratching your own itch, you were just building your own components and then open sourcing them. Is that how it started?
[Guest] 基本上是这样。我在 2000 年代初开始接触 Ruby，到了 2003 年我们开始做产品时，才算是真正拿它上强度。
Basically, I picked up Ruby in the early 2000s and really put it to the test in 2003 when we started building.
[Guest] 开始做 Basecamp 的时候，我事先并没有被规定必须用什么来开发。在那之前，我做过很多客户项目，他们会说，嗯，我们这个要用 PHP 来做，因为我们有人懂这个，所以你就得用它。后来我们开始做自己的系统，做 Basecamp，我可以自由选择，所以我选了 Ruby。
building base camp and I did not have a mandate of what to use to build it prior to that I've been working for a lot of client projects that would say well we're building this in PHP because we have someone who knows that so this is what you have to use and then we were building our own system we're building base camp and I was free to choose so I chose Ruby
[Guest] 而在当时，Ruby 在 Web 应用这块几乎没什么工具，或者说工具非常少。所以我只能自己把整套东西做出来，后来这就变成了 Ruby on Rails。它现在依然发展得很好，我到现在也还深度参与其中。
And at the time, Ruby didn't have any tooling or not very much when it came to web applications. So I had to build it all myself. And that turned into Ruby on Rails, which is still going strong. I'm still very heavily involved with that.
[Guest] 我觉得从某种意义上说，Ruby on Rails 现在有点复兴的感觉，因为它是构建 Web 应用时 token 效率最高的方式之一。它和我们现在面对的 agent 工作流简直是天然契合。
I think in some ways, Ruby on Rails is having a little bit of a renaissance now that it is one of the most token efficient ways of building web apps. It's ideally suited for the agent workflows we're dealing with now.
[Guest] 当然，这种情况能持续多久还不好说。没准再过五分钟，所有 agent 就都开始写机器码或者汇编了，那这波可能也就结束了。不过至少眼下是这样。
Now, we'll see how long that lasts. Maybe all the agents are going to be writing machine code or assembler in about five minutes. So maybe that comes to an end. But for the moment,
[Guest] token 效率依然很重要，agent 产出的代码人类是否能看懂、能验证也依然很重要，不过这件事在某个时间点也可能会走到尽头。
token efficiency still matters and it still matters whether the agents produce code that humans are able to read and verify that may also come to an end at some point.
[Guest] 就目前来说，看到这类我为了满足自己需求而做的项目，能引起更大社区的共鸣，然后大家纷纷出现、想要帮忙，这一路真的很有意思。比如说 Umachi，它到现在也才存在了，怎么说呢，刚刚超过六个月。
As it is right now, it's been a fun ride to just see these kinds of projects where I'm scratching my own itch resonate with a much larger community of people who then show up and want to help. I mean, for Umachi, which has only been around for, what is that, just over six months now,
[Guest] 我们已经有，差不多 400 位贡献者给这个发行版提交过代码改动。除此之外，还有几万人安装了它，并把它当作自己的日常主力系统。所以我一直很喜欢那种发现新东西的感觉，
we have, what, 400 contributors who've made code changes to the distribution. And on top of that, we have tens of thousands of people who've installed it and used it as their daily driver. So I always love that discovery of something new,
[Guest] 那种像 Ruby 一样新鲜、独特又让人受启发的东西。
novel, and inspiring like Ruby.
[Guest] 或者说，把一个从 91 年就存在的操作系统说成是“发现”，听起来有点怪。但对很多人来说，Linux 现在确实就是那种新发现，因为他们以前并没有在自己的个人电脑上用过它。
Or it sounds weird to talk about discovery of an operating system that's been around since, what, 91? But for a lot of people, Linux now is that discovery because they have not been using it on their personal computer.
[Guest] 所以他们是第一次接触它。而对我来说，如果因为我把门槛稍微拉平了一点，让入门变得更容易，让默认安装出来的效果看起来就很惊艳，从而帮助新一批 Linux 用户，甚至是爱好者出现，那会让我特别开心。
So they're seeing it for the first time. And for me to help a new cohort of Linux users and hopefully even enthusiasts come to be because I'm flattening the curve a little bit, I'm making it easier to get started, I'm making the default installation just look amazing.
[Guest] 这样一来，他们不会觉得自己非得花上 100 个小时去折腾系统才能开始用，这真的很有意思。当然，另一件同样有意思的事是，这两样东西——Ruby、Rails，还有 Amachii——都不只是业余项目。我很喜欢业余项目，以后也一直会做，但我也喜欢把它们应用到商业里。所以在 37signals，我们基于 Ruby 和 Rails 建立起了一整套持续了 20 多年的业务，而现在我们也在开发者的大多数机器上运行 Linux。
instances that they don't feel like they have to invest 100 hours into tweaking the system to get going it's really fun but what's also fun of course is that both of these things both ruby and rails and amachii were not just hobby projects i love hobby product and i will always do those but i also like to apply them to business so at 37 signals we built an entire business for 20 plus years on top of ruby and rails we're now running linux
[Guest] 因为我们现在已经有了自己的发行版。
on the majority of developer machines because we now have our own distro.
[Host] 所以总的来说，我是说，大家是可以自己选的，对吧？
So Obacu on all, I mean, people can choose, right?
[Guest] 嗯，
Well,
[Host] 真的可以吗？
Can they?
[Guest] 某种程度上吧，算是。我们一开始是开放选择的。但到了某个阶段，这就不再合理了。就像你不可能在 37 Signal 里有人说，
sort of, kind of. We started with an open choice. And then at some point, it just doesn't make sense anymore. In the same way, it would not make sense for someone to be at 37 Signal and say,
[Guest] “我想用 Django 来写这个。我们要用 Python 和另一个框架”，哪怕你们明明用的是 Ruby on Rails，而且一直都是这么做的。所以我们从早期那种……
I want to write this thing in Django. We're going to use Python and this other framework, even if you have Ruby on Rails and you're doing that. So we pivoted from an early...
[Guest] 那种鼓励大家随便试试的状态转变了。我刚切到 Linux 的时候，他们会说，嘿，你想看看就看看。后来 Amachi 这边开始更认真推进之后，我就说，技术岗位这边大家都全面切过去吧。当然 iOS 开发者不算，但凡是做 Web 的、用 Ruby 的、做
the invitation to play around that was what when i first switched to linux they said like hey if you want to check it out check it out then when things got a little more serious with amachi i just said let's go all in for everyone who's on the technical side of things not the ios developers of course but anyone who's working with the web who's working with ruby who's doing
[Guest] DevOps 的，都应该用 Linux。首先，这样会更接近我们的生产环境。我们一直都是部署在 Linux 上的。从第一天起，我们服务端对开发者和系统运维来说就是 Linux 阵营。
DevOps, they should be on Linux because, first of all, that's closer to what we deploy. We've always deployed on Linux. We've been a Linux shop on the server side since day one for developers and system operators.
[Guest] 我其实觉得，离生产环境更近、对这些工具更熟悉，确实是个很实在的优势。再加上，当然，我们自己也在构建这个发行版，所以应该尽可能让更多人一起帮忙。
I actually think it is a material advantage to be closer to your production environment and just be more familiar with the tools. Then on top of that, of course, we're building this distribution and we should have as many hands help out as possible.
[Guest] 而且考虑到我是这家公司的 CTO，技术方向由我来定，而这就是我们要走的方向。
And given the fact that I'm the CTO of this company, I get to set the technical direction and this is the direction we're going.
[Host] 你能不能简单快速回顾一下，就是你们现在整体是怎么运转的、业务目前发展到什么阶段？你们一直在持续建设、持续发布各种新鲜、让人兴奋、很酷的东西，我记得最新的应该是 Fizzy。
can you just like do a like just a very short recap of of you know like how you can run right and right now where are you like where is the business as a whole and you know you keep you keep building you keep launching new and exciting and just cool stuff i think fizzy was the latest one
[Guest] 可以。32 Signals 成立于 1999 年，最开始是一家网页设计公司。然后我在 2001 年加入，也就是两年后，接下来的几年里。
Yes, so 32 Signals was founded in 1999. It started as a web design. Firm. And then I joined up in 2001, two years after, and for a couple of years.
[Guest] 我和 Jason 一起做这些咨询项目。后来到了 2003 年，我们开始做 Basecamp，并在 2004 年发布。实际上，它上线的时间不是在 Facebook 上线前一天，就是后一天，这个巧合还挺有意思的，我们算是同一时期、同一拨公司。大概一年之内，我们就意识到这东西开始起飞了，于是我们全职投入，把公司从咨询业务转成了一家软件公司。
collaborated with Jason on these consulting projects and then it was in 2003 we started to work on Basecamp released it in 2004 actually either the day after the day before Facebook went live which is kind of a funny coincidence that we were of that same time and cohort and within about a year we realized this thing was taking off and we went full-time and switched from being a consultancy to being a software company and
[Host] 太棒了。
Awesome.
[Guest] 到现在已经是 22 年前的事了，甚至还要更久一点。这期间我们发布了很多产品。Basecamp 是第一个，也一直是最大、最重要的那个，这点其实也挺有意思，因为你会……
that's now 22 years ago A little more than that, and in that time we've released a ton of products. Basecamp was the first. Remains the biggest and most important, which is also kind of funny because you...
[Guest] 有时候你可能会有一种错觉，觉得自己学得越多、经验越丰富，就会变得更聪明，也会有更好的点子。但其实不是。很多人的第一个点子就是最好的点子。我一点也不觉得丢脸地说，从商业角度客观来看，Basecamp 就是我们做过最好的点子。我也非常自豪，20 多年来我们一直让它持续发展、不断成长、保持活力。很少有软件公司，更别说软件产品了，能拥有这样的寿命和积淀。
sometimes perhaps have this delusion that as you learn more and as you get more experience you'll get smarter and you'll have better ideas and like no there's tons of people for whom their first idea was the best idea and i have no shame in saying that base camp was the best idea objectively in terms of a business that we've ever had and i'm incredibly proud that we've been able to keep that going and growing and flourishing for over 20 years very few you
[Guest] 不过这些年我们也尝试了很多东西，也取得过一些很不错的成功。我们在 2020 年推出了 hey.com，也就是我们的电子邮件服务。
do software companies, let alone software products, can boast of that longevity and legacy. But we've tried a ton of things over those years and had some other great successes. We launched hey.com, our email Yep. service back in 2020,
[Guest] 现在回头想想，这真是个疯狂的任务。这个领域几乎完全被单一玩家 Google 的 Gmail 统治。那可是
which was a crazy mission when you think about it. Here is a sector completely dominated by a single player, Google, with Gmail. That's
[Host] 70%，
70%,
[Guest] 一个很好的产品。
a good product.
[Host] 对。
yeah.
[Guest] 17 年来它其实没怎么变过，但确实一直很扎实。
It hasn't really changed in 17 years, but it was really solid.
[Guest] 而且很多人对它也完全满意。他们脑子里好像同时存在这样一种矛盾：一方面他们讨厌电子邮件，另一方面却又 somehow 没把这件事和自己正在用电子邮件联系起来，我觉得这很有意思。但不管怎样，我们推出了这个产品，它不仅是在和这样一个根基极深的产品竞争，而这个产品在市场份额上的掌控力，可能比我能想到的美国任何一个主要品类里的其他产品都更强。
and lots of people are perfectly content with it they think they hold this duality in their head where at once they both hate email but somehow don't connect it to the fact that they're using email which i find curious but either way we launched this that is not only a competitor to this very entrenched product that has probably a greater
[Guest] 我觉得 Gmail 大概占了所有电子邮件流量的 85%，这
grasp on market share in any major category than any other product i can come to mind of in the u.s i think gmail is something like 85 of all email traffic which
[Host] 对。
Yeah.
[Guest] 听起来很夸张，也许是 80%，高得离谱。基本上，图上就是 Gmail，然后其他所有东西都挤在一个特别小的角落里。所以我们当时想，我用了 Gmail 之后，其实从那时候起就一直在用。
sounds insane maybe it's 80 is incredibly high Basically, Gmail and then all the rest is in this tiny little part of the graph. So we thought that after using Gmail, I used it since.
[Guest] 我都不记得自己是什么时候注册的了。用了没几周，我就拿到了那种邀请码。那真是一次特别聪明的发布方式。之后我就一直在用。所以算下来，我用 Gmail 真的是用了 17 年左右。
I don't know when I signed up. A few weeks into it, I got one of those invite codes. That was a really clever launch. And I use it ever since. So that's literally 17 years or something of that of Gmail usage.
[Guest] 而在这段时间里，我对很多用起来不太符合我预期的地方，慢慢积累了不少看法。我们把这些想法都放进了一款新的软件产品里，前前后后花了将近两年时间开发，
And over that time, I built up a lot of opinions about things that didn't work quite like I would prefer it to work. And we put all those opinions into a new software product spent about almost two years developing it,
[Guest] 累计投入了数百万美元的研发资金，并在 2020 年夏天发布了它。顺便说一句，那可真是个发布产品的“好时机”。
millions of dollars in cumulative R&D funds and launched it in the summer of 2020, which, by the way. Time to launch a product.
[Guest] 2020 年本来就因为各种各样的原因不太顺，我们当时差不多是在想，能不能有那么一周，全世界别再这么疯狂了。我们终于挑了一周上线，结果接着就和 Apple 打了一场硬仗。
2020 wasn't great for a whole host of different reasons we were kind of trying to slot in a can there just be a week where the whole world is not just insane we finally picked a week we went live and then we had the battle of our lives with apple
[Host] 和 Apple 的那场事，我记得。
Without Apple, I remember that.
[Guest] 然后最终
and ultimately
[Guest] 他们
They
[Guest] 它
it
[Guest] 没有
didn't
[Guest] 最后变成
ended up
[Guest] 想要批准你的 app。
want to prove your app.
[Guest] 他们不愿意批准我们的 app，除非我们支付那笔过路费，也就是 30
they didn't want to prove our app unless we paid the toll fee the 30
[Guest] 2%。
2%.
[Guest] 他们基本上就是在说，你可以不上架 App Store，而对那样的邮件产品来说，这等于判了死刑。
and they were basically willing to say You can be in the App Store, which for an email product like that is a death sentence.
[Host] 对
Yes
[Guest] 你必须上移动端，而且不只是移动端，得是 iPhone。现在也是这样。付费用户里大多数都是 iPhone 用户，因为那是美国规模最大、
You have to be on not just mobile phones, but specifically the iPhone. This is true today. The majority of paying customers are iPhone users because that's the largest,
[Guest] 消费能力最强的市场，而美国又是全世界消费能力最强的软件市场。所以这门生意要想跑通，我们就必须上 iPhone。经过了两周来回拉扯、堪称史诗级的斗争之后。
most affluent market in the U.S. and the U.S. is the most affluent software market in the world. So for that business to work, we need to be on the iPhone. After a two-week epic struggle back and forth.
[Guest] 好在时间点卡得非常准，正好赶上 WWDC，那时候 Apple 大概也不想让自己看起来像是在碾压一个开发者的巨人
thankfully timed to perfection with wwdc where apple preferably didn't want to look like the goliath squashing a developer
[Host] 小 David。
Tiny David.
[Guest] 一个小开发者，最后我们还是被允许进去了，而 Apple 事后某种程度上也改写了规则，好让这件事说得通。嗯，这算是一次小胜利，不是最终的胜利，但至
tiny developer we ended up being allowed in and apple sort of rewrote the rules after the fact to make it fit um it was a small victory not the ultimate victory but at
[Host] 恭喜。
Congrats.
[Guest] 少它让我们能够留在那里，而它后来也取得了巨大的成功，部分原因是
least it allowed us to to be there and he ended up being an enormous success in part
[Guest] 讽刺的是，Apple 那两周给了我们铺天盖地的曝光。现在回头看，我觉得我不会再那样赌了，因为最坏结果本来就是零，对吧。就是，Apple 拒了我们的 app，我们拉来 200 个用户，然后这个 app 就死了。
ironically because apple gave us wall-to-wall coverage for two weeks when i look back upon that i think i wouldn't have gambled like that because the outcome would have been zero right like uh apple refuses our app we sign up 200 people and the app is dead
[Guest] 结果反而是，他们给了我们一场数百万美元级别的上线推广活动，还拿下了所有主流媒体的报道。最初那几周里，我们就注册了几万人。那真是个疯狂的时刻，但也特别让人满足。
What instead happened was they gave us a multi-million dollar launch campaign and coverage in all major media and we signed up tens of thousands of people in those first weeks. That was an insane event, but also very satisfying.
[Guest] 另一件让我很满足的事是，我真的很喜欢 hey，我每天都在用它。说到 Web 应用，我基本上最常用的是 Basecamp。我们所有协作性的工作都在那里完成。然后我的第二大应用，很多天里甚至是第一大应用，就是 hey。
The other satisfying thing was I just love hey, I use it every day. I basically use base camp in terms of web applications. That's where we do all our collaborative work. And then my number two app and many days it's my number one app is hey,
[Guest] 因为我所有事情几乎都在邮件里处理。我一直在和人沟通、写东西，很多事情都是通过邮件完成的，很多人也都这样。所以让这件事变成一种愉快的体验，处在一个舒服的环境里，真的很重要。
because I just do all my stuff in email. I am constantly communicating with people I'm writing, I'm doing a lot of stuff in email, as many people do and having that be a pleasurable experience and a nice environment and
[Guest] 而且我的收件箱也更像是一块神圣空间，不像 Gmail 那样，世界上完全陌生的人只要你开着通知——而且默认就是开着的——就能让你口袋里的手机嗡嗡响。我觉得这简直太离谱了，对吧？
My inbox being a little more sacred than what happens with Gmail where total strangers around the world can just make your pocket buzz if you have notifications turned on, which they are by default, just seems insane to me, right?
[Guest] 居然有人可以直接接触到我每天最重要的优先事项清单之一，好像任何人都能往上面塞东西？太离谱了。总之，
This idea that there's direct access to one of my most important daily priority lists, like anyone can put something on that? Insane. Anyway,
[Guest] hey 不会这样。我们有筛选器。在你明确说“我想收到这个人的邮件”之前，谁都进不了你的收件箱。而大多数时候，我对大多数人都会说不。
hey doesn't do that. We have the screener. No one gets to reach your inbox before you've said, I want to hear from this person. And most of the time I say no to most people,
[Guest] 对吧？邮件会先进入筛选区，我们有点赞和点踩。点赞：我愿意收这个人的邮件。点踩：我再也不想收到这个人的邮件。
right? Like things end up in the screen and we have thumbs up. I will hear from this person. Thumbs down. I'll never hear from that person again.
[Host] 对，我就是这么联系到你的。我的意思是，我不太确定我们当时有没有在 X 上互相关注，但我给你发了邮件，因为你的邮箱地址是公开的，而你的筛选器显然起作用了，因为它给了我一个点赞。
well this is how i reached out i mean we were i'm not sure we were connected on on x but i sent an email because your email is out there and your screener seems to have worked because it gave me the thumbs up
[Guest] 确实有用，因为筛选的人就是我。所以甚至都没有 AI 来判断我到底想不想收到你的消息。因为事实证明，这件事其实……
It did because the screen is me. So there's not even AI trying to suss out whether I want to hear from you or not. Because what turns out to be true is it's...
[Guest] 其实一点也不麻烦，每天花一次时间过一遍你的筛选列表，然后点个赞或踩就行，因为世界上也没那么多人。而且如果你把那些烦人的、
It's actually not that onerous to once a day go through your screener and say thumbs up or down because there aren't that many people in the world. And if you say no to the annoying,
[Guest] 死缠烂打的销售拒掉——他们在 Gmail 里居然能把你的收件箱翻来覆去看上七遍——那工作量就小多了。而且我得说，这种感觉还挺爽的，因为我以前用 Gmail 的时候，
pestering salespeople who within Gmail manage to read your inbox seven times, then the workload is much less. And it's very satisfying, I would say, too, because when I was using Gmail,
[Guest] 我总会被他们那套销售话术给套进去，而他们显然就是靠这个。比如你回信说，不。就是，不用了，谢谢，我没兴趣，然后
I would get roped into this sales tactic that they, of course, rely on, which is that like you write back and say like, no. like no thank you i'm not interested and
[Host] 然后你就会
And then you have
[Guest] 他们
they
[Guest] 就会
the
[Guest] 会
would
[Guest] 处理掉。
cover.
[Guest] 又会再来回复你，
respond again and
[Host] 对。
Yes.
[Guest] 这时候你就会觉得，等等，我是不是有义务回复这个人？我多少会觉得好像是有。然后有时候我最后还真会去写回复。就算我不回，他们还是能进到我的收件箱里，所以我下周还会再收到他们的邮件。他们都有一整套滴灌式营销流程，妈的，人人都这样，对吧。任何一次外联都不是一封邮件，而是七封。要是你表现出任何一点“还活着”的迹象，那可能就变成 52 封了。事情就是这么运作的。可要是我点一次踩，以后就再也不会收到那个人的邮件了，真的神奇，神奇到
now you feel like wait am i not obligated to respond to this person i kind of feel like i am and occasionally i would end up writing and even if i wouldn't write they still have access to my inbox so i would hear from them again next week they have a whole drip campaign they all fucking do right that any outreach is seven emails it's not one emails it's seven emails and if you show any sign of life it's probably 52 that's just not how it works and hey i say thumbs down one time never hear from that person again it's actually amazing how
[Host] 神奇的是，你一下子就能把自己的花园修整出来。
Amazing how quickly you can curate your garden from that.
[Guest] 把杂草除掉，然后突然之间，剩下的就全是漂亮的花。突然间，邮件不再是一件苦差事了，你甚至会想去闻闻玫瑰。突然间，最后进到我邮箱里的大多数东西，都是我想看的，都是我想听到的人发来的。这其实就是我们做 hey 时最根本的使命：我们能不能让电子邮件重新变得讨人喜欢？有太多人讨厌电子邮件了，因为这些系统做得太差了，因为它们建立在一个最初的前提上：电子邮件不过是大学里用的东西，
weed and then suddenly there's just beautiful flowers suddenly email is not a chore so you want to go smell the roses suddenly the majority of things that end up in my email are things i want to read it's from people i want to hear from and that was really the fundamental mission for us with hey can we make email lovable again email is so hated by so many people because the systems are so poor because they're based on the original premise that email is just what universities use
[Guest] 是给科学家彼此交流用的，而科学家通常都很有礼貌，不会为了卖一个蠢 app 连着骚扰你 52 次。不会，他们是克制的、得体的，对吧。很美好的理想，很美好的想法，很美好的协议设计，都是为那样的规范和那样的人准备的。可一旦把它放到更广阔的现实世界里，你就会发现，不是每个人都具备那样的规范和礼貌，尤其是销售一介入之后，
used for scientists to talk to each other and scientists have really good manners and will not pester you 52 times about some stupid app they want to sell you no they're respectful and beautiful right beautiful ideal beautiful thought beautiful protocol design for those norms and those people then you let it into the world at large and you realize not everyone is endowed with such norms and such politeness and especially when salespeople get involved
[Guest] 销售一介入，你就需要更好的防御机制。对我、对我们、对我们的很多客户来说，hey 就是那道防线。它让人重新爱上电子邮件。而且我觉得，拥有一个宏大的“为什么”其实真的很重要。
get involved so you need better defenses and for me and for us and for all our many customers hey is that defense it is a way to love email again and i find that it's really important actually to have a grand why
[Host] 这可以一直追溯到 Viktor Frankl，《Man's Search for Meaning》里讲的意义。
This is all the way back to Viktor Frankl, the meaning of man.
[Guest] 找到一个“为什么”，能让你在寒冷、不舒服、又烦人的时候，依然愿意顶着风雪往前走。用电脑做产品时，很多事情就是这样：不舒服，还烦人。现在，
Finding a why allows you to walk through the snow when it's cold and uncomfortable and annoying, which many things are when you're building with computers. They are called uncomfortable and annoying. Now,
[Guest] 当然，大多数时候不该都是这样，但偶尔确实会遇到。如果你心里有一个特别强的“为什么”——我们为什么要做这个？这是给谁做的？我们到底是在
it shouldn't be that most of the time, but occasionally that would be there. And if you have a really strong why, why are we building this? Who is it for? What are we?
[Guest] 努力做什么，来让这个世界变得更好——哪怕没那么宏大，只是让人们更喜欢用 email——那你背起那些不得不扛的负担时，就会轻松很多，也会享受很多，只要你能这样去建立这件事。
trying to do to improve the world even if that's not more grand than just letting people love email it's a lot easier and it's a lot more enjoyable to then carry whatever burdens you got to pack if you can set it up that way
[Host] 这正好也是聊聊我们本季赞助商 WorkOS 的好时机。强烈的“为什么”会推动你做出伟大的产品。但当你把产品做出来，开始卖给企业客户之后，他们会期待像 SAML、SSO、Directory Sync 这样的能力。
This is a good time to talk about our season sponsor, WorkOS. Having a strong why is what gets you to building something great. But after you build it and start selling it to enterprise customers, they expect things like SAML, SSO, Directory Sync.
[Host] 还有审计日志和细粒度权限。这些都不是小功能，而是完整的系统。构建和维护这些系统可能要花上好几个月。WorkOS 提供面向企业就绪的认证和用户管理 API，让你几天内就能搞定，而不是几个月，
Think audit logs and fine-grained permissions. And those are not small features, they're systems. Systems that can take months to build and maintain. Work OS gives you APIs for enterprise-ready auth and user management in days instead of months,
[Host] 而且这一切都被设计得能干净利落地融入你的产品。这就是为什么 OpenAI、Anthropic 和 Cursor 这样的公司都在用 WorkOS。专注于打造你的产品，把企业基础设施交给 WorkOS。
all designed to fit cleanly into your product. That's why companies like OpenAI and Tropic and Cursor run on Work OS. Focus on building your product, let Work OS handle the enterprise infrastructure.
[Host] 好，接下来我们回到 David，以及旧思维方式和新思维方式的对比。
With this, let's get back to David and the old way of thinking versus the new way of thinking.
[Host] 从开发者的角度来说，你能不能跟我讲讲你们当时是怎么把它做出来的？你刚说花了两年，但一开始只是一个人还是两个人在做？我敢说在技术上你们肯定大量用了 Ruby on Rails，然后我猜可能也做了一些原生开发之类的。不过两年还是感觉很久，尤其你也知道，你们公司规模小、动作灵活，你自己又是很厉害的开发者，也招得到很棒的开发者，结果一转眼就两年了。到底是什么花了这么久？当然，这产品确实很漂亮，不过对吧。
putting our your developer hat on like can you talk talk me through on how how you built it you said it was two years but was it just one or two people starting to build it i'm sure as tech you obviously must have used ruby on rails a lot and then i i don't probably some some native stuff as well but the two years seems a lot especially because you know you're you're a small company you're nimble you're a great developer i'm you hire great developers suddenly it's been two years what took so long for and of course it's a beautiful product but right
[Guest] 对。乍一看，作为开发者，我们可能都会有一种想法：两年，再加上一支很有天赋的团队。
Right. On the surface, I think as developers, we might have this thing where I look at it as like two years with a talented team.
[Guest] 这基本就是 Hacker News 对所有东西的经典吐槽，对吧：这玩意儿我一个周末就能做出来。Dropbox 当年就很有名，大家都说“这个我一个周末就能做出来”。最初 iPod 发布的时候也是，什么 5GB、没 Wi‑Fi、反正各种配置都不怎么样，速度还不如 Nomad 之类的。所以我能理解这种想法，因为我自己也有同样的本能反应。
that's the hacker news quip to basically everything right like i could have built that in a weekend i mean famously stated with dropbox that i could have built that in a weekend we could have at the original ipod when it launched it was like five gigabit uh no wi-fi uh whatever less speed than nomad lane so i get that because i also have that same instinct
[Guest] 我觉得这就是我们开发者的傲慢，我们
i think that is our hubris as developers we
[Guest] 这
It
[Guest] 种想法
think
[Guest] 就是这样，对吧？
is, right?
[Guest] 我们觉得自己像神一样，什么都能在极短时间内做出来。而且你确实可以，现在做个原型，速度比一个周末还快，对吧？几个小时内我们就应该能做出一个
we are gods and we can make anything happen in no time at all and you totally could you can make a prototype happen in these days faster than faster than a weekend right like in a few hours we should be able to have
[Host] 直接启动一个 agent 就行。对。
Just kick off an agent. Yeah.
[Guest] 真正搞清楚你到底想做什么，往往要花更久；而做到一个值得发布的东西，还要更久。至少对我们是这样，我觉得任何真正做出好东西的人，基本也都是这样。最初做 HEY 的时候，技术这边就只有我一个人。其实我们大多数重要产品一开始都是这么做的：要么只有我，有时候再加一个开发，但在我们真正搞出雏形之前，团队都非常非常小。
figuring out what you actually want to build takes a lot longer and arriving at something that's worth publishing takes longer still at least it does for us and i think it does for anyone who arrives at anything good and the original hey construction was just me on the technical side this is actually how we've started majority of our major products is either it's just me sometimes it's one additional developer but is a tiny tiny team until we have
[Guest] 在有了雏形、有了架构、也有了产品要往哪走的方向之前，我发现如果你往一个还不确定的方向里硬塞一堆人，反而会更慢。你要是连自己想要什么都不知道，就算给你一百万人，也做不出来。你得先想清楚自己要什么。这个我们等会儿可以再聊，不过 AI 最近的进展，确实正在非常剧烈地改变这件事。现在更快就能搞清楚：我到底想要什么。但是——
a shape until we have an architecture and we have a direction of where the product is going to go i've found that you actually go slower if you pour a bunch of people into a direction that is uncertain if you don't know what you want a million people is not going to build it for you you have to figure out what you want we can talk about this later but this is where ai's very recent progress is changing things dramatically it is now quicker to arrive at what do i want but
[Guest] 但做 HEY 的时候，一开始是我，后来是 Jason，再加一个设计师、两个设计师，非常非常小的团队，一直在摸这个产品的形状。你要是想挑战 Gmail，不能只是做一个蓝色版的 Gmail，那没人会买账，也没人会感兴趣。它必须得——
for hey it was me and then it was Jason and one designer two designers very very small team trying to figure out the shape trying to figure out if you're taking on Gmail you can't just do Gmail in blue no one's gonna buy that no one's gonna be interested in that it's gotta be
[Guest] 得有新意。其实不只是有新意，还得足够好。它得解决一些用户甚至都还没明确说出口的 Gmail 问题。因为大家对 Gmail 的抱怨通常是“我讨厌电子邮件”，但就像我们刚才说的，这其实有点把方向带偏了。
novel which means it's well not just novel it's gotta be good it's gotta solve problems that people haven't even articulated they have with gmail because the articulation people have of their problems with gmail is i hate email which as we talked about is a bit of a misdirection
[Guest] 我的看法是，你讨厌的其实是 Gmail，而且不只是 Gmail，还包括大多数还建立在那套老路子上的邮件系统——比如任何人都能直接进入你的收件箱之类的。
My contention is you hate Gmail and not just Gmail, but most email systems build on the old way of anyone has access to your inbox and all that stuff.
[Guest] 但要把这些想明白，把产品的形状摸出来，是需要时间的。而且这种过程本身也挺有意思，你会反复琢磨它，同时你手上也没有无限的产能。最初的 Basecamp 也是这么做出来的，技术这边也只有我一个人。
But figuring that out, figuring the shape out takes a while and is also fun to do in this way where you noodle with it and you don't have infinite capacity. The original base camp is built the same way. It was just me on the technical side.
[Host] 这算是一种 Shape Up 的思路吗？
Is this a shape-up mentality?
[Guest] 这里面有一种 Shape Up 式的思路，想要去做到这一点。
There's shape up thinking in trying to.
[Guest] 其实是要赋予设计师一种关于“它该怎么运作”的意图，而不只是“它该长什么样”。当然，也要弄清楚它该怎么呈现。产品应该是漂亮的、独特的、有吸引力的，诸如此类，这也需要时间。但首先最重要的是搞清楚它该怎么运作，找出核心点在哪里，最重要的部分是什么，再把这些都梳理开。不过在 hey 上，和我们做过的所有主要产品一样，我们一开始都是一个极小的团队，往往程序这边就只有一个人
actually endow the designer with an intention of how should it work not just how should it look and figuring out it's also how it should look products should be beautiful and they should be unique and appealing and so forth so that also takes time but figuring out how it should work is primary figuring out where's the epicenter what's the most important part and teasing all that apart but with hay as with all the major products we've done we start with an absolutely tiny team often just one individual
[Guest] 设计这边再配一两个人，然后我们就一路推进、推进、推进、推进。突然某个时刻一下子通了，我们会觉得：这个不错，这里面有东西。然后团队会稍微爬坡，再多加几个人。等到进入最后大概
on the programming side and then one or two individuals on the design side and then we go we go we go we go suddenly something clicks and we go like this is good there's something here and then there's a bit of a ramp we take on a few more people and then when we get within maybe the last
[Guest] 20%的阶段时，我们就会说，好，现在我们已经知道地形长什么样了，如果大家一起上，就能快得多。
20 we go okay now we know what the terrain looks like we can go way faster if everyone piles in so
[Host] 有一点特别有意思，你可能已经习以为常了，但这和大多数拿了 VC 资金的创业公司——我对这种模式很熟——以及 Uber、Facebook 这些大公司都非常不一样。那些地方启动项目的方式通常是，先由产品经理来负责，可能再配上半个设计师
one thing that is super interesting and you might take it for granted but it's very different to how most startups that raise vc money which i'm very familiar with and and big companies uber facebook you name it the way projects would start there is you take the product manager who works with maybe maybe half a designer
[Host] 先把 spec 写出来，然后开发人员后面才介入。而我现在听到的、对我来说很新鲜的一点是，你们会先上一个或两个设计师，再加一个开发。包括你们怎么看待设计师这件事——你们最近还招了一位设计师 Zoltan，实际上我还在和他聊，呃，关于
and comes up with a spec and then developers get involved later and what i'm hearing what is very novel to me is you take one or two designers and a developer how you think about designers even you recently hired a designer zoltan actually who i'm i'm chatting with uh on
[Guest] 哦，太好了。
Oh, great.
[Host] 关于
on
[Guest] 哦，
Oh,
[Host] 他那一派的。
the he's side
[Guest] 很棒。
awesome.
[Host] 你人很好，但我的感觉是，你看待设计师的方式，和行业里大多数人的看法可能有点不一样。
you're a great guy but my sense is you think of designers a little bit different than potentially the rest of the industry does
[Guest] 确实非常不一样。在 37 Signals，设计师不只是来把规格说明做得好看。
We very much do. Designers at 37 Signals are not just here to make a spec look good.
[Host] 做漂亮点。
Look pretty
[Guest] 他们的职责是去发现规格说明本来应该是什么样，从很多方面来说，他们其实就是产品经理。他们是——
They're here to find what the specs should be their product managers in many ways. They are the
[Guest] 在很多情况下，他们负责找出“怎么做”和“为什么做”；有时是通过推导，有时是根据客户反馈，还有些时候纯粹靠直觉，然后把这些提炼成“我们该做什么”以及“它应该怎么运作”。除此之外，他们还要负责把它做出来：负责 CSS，负责 HTML，而且很多时候还会参与一点 JavaScript 和 Ruby 代码，把东西做成真正可用的功能。而现在——
finders of the how and the why in many cases deducing in some cases customer feedback in other cases just pure intuition and distilling that into what should we build and how should it work and then on top of that they're also responsible for building it they're responsible for doing the css they're responsible for doing the html they're quite often responsible at least dabbling in the javascript and the ruby code to get to something functional and now
[Guest] 有了 agent acceleration，他们会把整件事都做完。不一定是最终会被合并进去的那个版本，但至少会把完整方案做出来，也就是最终应该长什么样、设计该是什么样子。
With agent acceleration, they do the whole thing. Not necessarily as it will be merged, but the whole thing in terms of here's the final shape. and design of what it should look like.
[Guest] 但我确实觉得，我们在这方面很特别。我们在招设计师的时候也发现，很多在其他公司工作的设计师，并不习惯同时戴上产品经理这顶帽子，
But I do think we are very peculiar in this sense. And we have found this when we've been trying to hire designers, that many designers working at other companies are not used to also wearing the product manager hat,
[Guest] 去想清楚我们到底该做什么，同时还要戴上实现者这顶帽子，把它落实成 CSS 和 HTML。我发现，当你把这三顶帽子合到一个人身上时，这个人就会真正了解自己在使用的材料。
figuring out what we should build, and wearing the implementation hat, shaping it into CSS and HTML. I found that when you combine these three hats into one, you have an individual who know the materials they're working with. with.
[Guest] 知道它们能怎么延展，知道接缝该往哪个方向裁，因此也就能很自然地顺着互联网这块布料来工作。当你直接用 CSS 工作、直接用 HTML 工作时，
Know how they stretch, know which way the seam is supposed to be cut, and therefore works natively with the fabric of the internet. When you're working directly in CSS, when you're working directly in HTML,
[Guest] 你就会更能体会这种媒介本身想要什么。我觉得如果你是珠宝设计师，大概也是一样的。你应该了解黄金的特性，知道它怎么弯折、强度如何。一个
you're just much more in tune with what this medium wants. And I find that that's probably quite similar if you're a jewelry designer. You should know the properties of gold. You should know how it bends and the strength. An
[Host] 什么
What
[Guest] 建筑师应该
architect should
[Guest] 你可以怎么做
you could do with
[Guest] 有
have
[Guest] 那种东西。
that.
[Guest] 某种……
some...
[Guest] 某种对承重结构之类的工程理解。当然不用到建筑师把整套东西都设计完、然后我们才开始浇筑混凝土的程度；你还是会有工程师来帮你。但你越理解自己在使用的材料，就越有可能做出顺着材料纹理来的东西，因此最后会让人觉得对、觉得舒服。顺便快速跳到 Apple，我觉得这也是原因之一，为什么
some engineering understanding of load-bearing structures and so on not to the degree that the architect is just going to design the whole thing and then we start pouring concrete you still have engineers helping you out but the more you understand the materials you're working with the more you're likely to come up with something that cuts along the grain and therefore ends up feeling correct feeling good just a quick hop to apple i think this is one of the reasons why
[Guest] 为什么一些老牌超级粉丝，比如 Daring Fireball，还有其他人，呃，Gruber，会对新的方向感到失望。因为 Apple 过去代表的是那种设计极其精妙的原生 Mac 应用，而这种东西正在消亡——现在基本已经死了。现在我们有 Electron，这个也可以聊，它在我看来被黑得太过了；当然也有很多做得很烂的实现，但本质上它就是把网页装进一个盒子里。
why some of the historic super fans like daring fireball and others uh gruber have been disappointed by the new direction is that apple used to stand for these exquisitely designed native mac applications which is a dying breed like they're essentially dead now we have electron which we can talk about that too it gets way too much hate in my book there's crappy implementation of that but it's just a web in a box
[Guest] 一个盒子。但失去那种感觉之所以让人失望，我觉得说的还是同一件事：Mac 以及它那种原生的手感，是有延展性的。比如按钮的位置，凡是你会称作原生应用的东西，要么感觉很做作。
The box. But the disappointment with losing that sense, and I think it's about the same thing, that the Mac, its native feel has a stretch to it. Like the button placement, everything you would call a native application either feels synthetic.
[Guest] 要么就感觉很真实。而今天几乎全都是做作的，已经没剩下什么真实感了。我觉得对 Web 也是一样。只是现在 Web 是一个大得多得多的平台，所以它也因此得到了更多关注。
or it feels authentic. And today it's all synthetic. There's nothing authentic about it left. And I think for the web, it's the same thing. Now, the web is a much, much larger platform and therefore it's gotten much more attention.
[Guest] 所以投入在这种品质上的人要多得多。但在大公司里，这种动态极其罕见，几乎等于不存在。我觉得其中一部分以后会改变。
So there are way more people working on that quality of it. But at the large companies, it's exceptionally rare to non-existent to have that kind of dynamic. I think some of that is going to change.
[Guest] Agent acceleration 会让设计师在这些方面变得更有能力。所以整个行业正在一点点靠近我们的基本立场。这也挺有意思的，因为在编程这边也是一样。
Agent acceleration is going to empower designers to be more capable in these ways. So the industry is coming a little towards our fundamental stance, which is funny, too, because the same is true in the programming side.
[Guest] 我刚才说 Basecamp 在上线时，编程这边基本上就是我一个人做出来的，这件事在很长一段时间里听起来都像是——
When I talked about Basecamp being a product of just me on the programming side for launch, that for so long sounded.
[Guest] 不够有野心，甚至不对，甚至在互联网上有些人会觉得你是在撒谎。他们会说，对啊，但如果没有一个大得多的团队，你根本不可能做出任何真正的、有意义的、规模大的东西，因为那最终只会是个玩具产品，对吧。而我从一开始的看法就是，这当然是胡扯，因为你们只是没用过 ruby on rails，你们只是没体验过用更好的工具所能带来的那种加速。
unambitious or even wrong or even to the point of lying from some quarters of the internet we're like yeah but you can't build anything real anything meaningful anything big unless you have a team that's much larger because it's just going to be a toy product a product right and my insight from the start was that's of course bullshit because you just haven't used ruby on rails you just haven't used the acceleration that's possible if you use better tools you
[Guest] 现在，我们都开始意识到这一点了。我们意识到，哦，原来如果你用 agent acceleration，一个人其实真的能做出高——
Now, we're all realizing that. We're realizing, oh, so if you use agent acceleration, a single individual actually can build something high
[Guest] 这就是
That's what
[Guest] 有价值的东西。
valuable.
[Host] 就像你说的，像一个团队一样。
you said, it's like a team.
[Guest] 对。而且看到整个行业也在慢慢转向这种想法，真的很有意思，就像，哦——
Yes. And that's just fun to see that like the industry is coming towards, oh,
[Guest] 更小的团队更好，因为这样一来，你在沟通成本那条对数曲线上省下来的成本就开始变得很可观了。而这也正是我们也许可以聊聊的一点：agent acceleration 正在真正改变这种。
smaller teams are better because now the cost savings you have on the logarithmic curve on communication cost starts to be relevant. And this is one of the things maybe we can talk about this where agent acceleration is really changing the.
[Guest] 初级开发者和高级开发者之间的利益平衡。
Bargain between junior developers and senior developers.
[Host] 我们来聊聊这个。不过在进入这个话题之前，我感觉你非常看重软件工程作为一门手艺，这一点很明显，但我还感受到，你也很看重设计。
Let's talk about this. But before we go into that, do I feel that you very much value software engineering as a craft, which is very obvious, but what I'm sensing is you're valuing design.
[Host] 用户体验设计、软件设计，就是那种你知道的，做出让人感觉很好的东西，不管是软件还是硬件，你也把这当作一门手艺，而且你会主动去寻找这些东西。我这样感觉对吗？
user experience design designing on software design like you know like building stuff that feels good may that be software hardware you also value that as a craft and and you look for it like these two things do i sense this correctly
[Guest] 非常认同。我的意思是，我觉得美感就是真理。一个东西如果很美，它很可能就是对的。我觉得这在数学里是这样，在物理里也是这样。
Hugely. I mean, I think aesthetics is truth. When something is beautiful, it's likely to be correct. I think this is true in mathematics. This is true in physics.
[Guest] 在很多不同领域里都是这样：当你最终得到某个东西，而它具备了正确的审美品质时。
This is true in a lot of different domains that when you arrive at something that has the correct aesthetic quality.
[Guest] 就好像我们内心有一种直觉，会把我们引向那种美的层次，因为它同时也恰好是正确的、高贵的，也是值得追求的。我也相信，这正是让人快乐的东西。被美丽、
It's like we have an intuition that guides us towards that level of beauty because it also happens to be correct and noble and something to aspire for. I also happen to believe it's what makes people happy. Being surrounded by beautiful,
[Guest] 功能良好的物件所环绕，是幸福感的一个关键部分。其实，我也可以反过来说。焦虑和挫败感的一大来源之一。
well-functioned objects is a key part of happiness. In fact, I'll put it in a negative way too. One of the great sources of anxiety and frustration.
[Guest] 就是当一切都烂透了的时候：什么都卡，触控界面没反应，动不动就得重启；你打电话给旅行代理，他们也办不了事，因为他们那套又老又烂的 cobalt 系统根本不让他们操作。这个世界到处都不只是“劣化”——也就是那些原本好的东西变差了——而是干脆就是差，纯粹地糟糕透顶。我觉得这已经成了……
is when everything is shit when everything is laggy when that touch interface doesn't register when you have to restart it when you're calling a travel agent they can't do something because their old shitty cobalt system won't let them right the world is full of not just in shitification that is things that went from being good to being bad to just plain bad just plain awful and i think it is a
[Guest] 一种让整个文明都感到萎靡的重要来源。要是我们身边有更多更美的物件、更多更美的系统，我们真的可以把人类幸福感的基线整体抬高。
a serious source of malaise for civilization. That we could literally raise the bar of human happiness if we were surrounded by more beautiful items, more beautiful systems,
[Guest] 这里说的美，既包括外在审美层面的品质，也同样包括内在审美层面的品质，因为我发现这两者通常是完全和谐一致的。
both in the sense of its aesthetic exterior qualities, but just as much in terms of its aesthetic interior qualities, because I find those two things are usually in perfect harmony.
[Guest] Steve Jobs 之所以会在意盒子里面的样子，是因为他凭直觉知道……
The reason why Steve Jobs cared about the inside of the box was because he intuitively knew that...
[Guest] 会在意电路板布局的人，也会在意用户界面的细节；也会在意打开机箱时的人体工学。所以我觉得这里面有一种……
that the kind of people who care about the layout of the print board will be the kind of people who sweat the details on the user interface will be the kind of people who sweat the ergonomics of opening the case so i think there's
[Guest] 本质上你别无选择：如果你是那种会被审美吸引的人——而我觉得其实每个人都是，只是自觉程度不同——那你就会想把一切都做得更美。对我来说，Ruby 尤其是一门具有奠基意义的语言，因为在我看来，它能产出最美的代码，几乎都没有什么竞争对手。当然，也有别的东西会以某种方式显得很美，比如我觉得……
essentially no choice if you are a person who is attracted to this aesthetics which i think is everyone there's just varying levels of awareness about whether you are or not but that you want to make it all beautiful and for me ruby in particular has been this seminal language because it produces the most beautiful code in my book there's barely even competition like there are other things that can be beautiful in a way like i find
[Guest] 比如看 Smalltalk，就很美，它的极简主义非常漂亮，但那不是我想住进去的房子。
Looking at small talk, for example, very beautiful in its minimalism, but not the house I want to live in.
[Guest] Ruby 才是我想住进去的房子，因为它有那种审美品质，同时又不会在理念上特别僵化，这一点也非常罕见。我现在更常看到——前面其实也提到过——当一个人以这种方式痴迷某件事时，往往会变得有点狭隘，这是代价，是必须付出的成本。而我觉得 Ruby 不知怎么做到了既视野宽广，同时又在这件事上高度专注，不过……
is the house i want to live in because it's got that aesthetic quality while not being rigid about its ideology which is a very rare aspect too i more often find now we can refer to i've again is that when someone is obsessed in this way they are a little narrow-minded like that's the trade-off that's the price and i find that ruby has somehow managed to be both broad scoped yet also intensely focused on on this but
[Guest] 总的来说，我们必须拥有美好的东西。我们必须使用美好的工具。我们必须产出优美、流畅的交互。这就是我们作为手艺人应该如何看待自己：我们在乎打磨细节，直到再也没有任何毛刺。
Overall, we have to have beautiful things. We have to work with beautiful tools. We have to produce beautiful, fluid interactions. This is how we should see ourselves as craftspeople, that we care about polishing it until there are no splinters left.
[Host] AI 正在怎样改变你的工作方式？你觉得它又是怎样改变你的手艺的？或者这么说吧，还是回到这个“手艺”本身——你在 37 Signals 招的人，也同样在乎设计和软件工艺的质量。
How is AI changing how you work? And how do you think it's changing your craft? Or just let's just talk about the craft of, again, you're hiring people in 37 Signals who similarly care about design and software craft quality.
[Host] 它正在怎样改变你从这门手艺里获得的东西，或者说，它在哪些方面让它变得更好或更糟？我想先从这个开始：你的看法是怎么变的？因为你上一次比较深入地谈这个，是在 Lex Friedman 的播客上，
How is changing what you get out of the craft or how it's making it better or worse in some ways? I just want to start with like, how has your view changed? Because the last time you talked in length about this that was on Lex Friedman's podcast,
[Host] 而且你当时——而且也完全有理由——对 AI 还是非常怀疑。那时候工具完全不是现在这一套，也没这么好用。我记得你在那期里对它批评得挺狠的，但这之后情况已经变了。
and you were still rightfully so very skeptical of. of AI it was a different set of tools it didn't work as well and I think you went there bashing it pretty hard but things have changed since
[Guest] 这里面有个很微妙的点，也许这么说有点像在为自己开脱，但我其实不觉得我的观点变了。变的是环境和事实。我在那期节目里以及很多其他文章里，从一开始就强调过这一点：
This is a nuanced point, and maybe it's self-serving, but I don't actually think my opinions have changed. What have changed is the circumstances and the facts, which is something I called out on that show and in many other writings was right from the get-go,
[Guest] 我当时就看得出来，我们手上出现了某种新的、前所未有的东西，它会改变很多事情。
I could see that we had something new and novel here that was going to change things.
[Guest] ChatGPT 在三年前上线时，很明显、也毫无疑问——哪怕在当时——都是那种你会在时间线上专门标记出来的事件。
ChatGPT, its launch, what, three years ago, was clearly and obviously even at the time something you would mark on a timeline.
[Host] 对
Yeah
[Guest] 你会觉得，计算机科学史上，甚至整个人类世界里所有重要的事都摆在这儿了。结果，哇，ChatGPT 发布了。然后你开始用这种方式和计算机交互，看着它们进行推理，
You're like, here are all the important things that happened in the history of computer science or the world. Yoinks, there is the launch of ChatGPT. And interacting with computers in this way and seeing them reason,
[Guest] 虽然“推理”这个词可能现在还有争议，但对我来说，很明显，这些东西聪明得离谱。
even if that's still a disputed term, perhaps, but to me, it seemed obvious that these things were freaking smart.
[Guest] 很多方面都比我聪明。至于这种聪明到底是来自参数权重，还是数据素养之类的——我们连人类意识是怎么运作的都不知道，对人类的智慧或智能是怎么运作的也几乎不了解。
smarter than me in many ways whether those smarts came from parenting weights and data literacy so what we don't know how human consciousness works we don't know how human wisdom or intelligence works barely
[Guest] 所以，别那么武断地下定义，认定什么才算意识，什么才算智能。至少对我来说，这种区分没什么实际意义，哪怕拿来思考挺有意思。
So let's not be so categorical about what constitutes consciousness or intelligence. At least I find no utility in that distinction, even if it's fun to ponder.
[Guest] 但我在早期模型和早期交互体验里发现的，是那种自动补全式的东西，是你编辑器里的 co-pilot 和 cursor，老是在猜你下一个要输入的字符。
But what I found with the early models and the early ergonomics where it was autocomplete, where it was co-pilot and cursor in your editor trying to guess the next character.
[Host] 它会有点打断你的思路，对吧？
it would be something in littering it, right?
[Guest] 对，我觉得特别烦人。感觉就像……我们明明在试着对话，你却不让我把一句话说完，你一直在
Yes, I found it infuriating. I found it as... we're trying to have a conversation you won't let me finish the sentence you're constantly trying
[Host] 打断。
Interrupt.
[Guest] 你想表达的是这个吗，你想表达的是这个吗？你就像在说，闭嘴行不行，让我把一个想法说完。我当时觉得，就算它偶尔确实能加快一点速度，它出错的频率也高得离谱，以至于那种“加速”反而让人烦。哪怕从总体上看它可能是正收益——但对我来说并不是，或者也许是我放弃得太早了——反正我就是很不喜欢那种体验。
was this what you meant was this what you meant you're like shut the hell up can i just finish a thought and i thought even if it is capable of occasionally accelerating it's also wrong so often that that acceleration feels like a nuisance even if it's somehow net positive which it wasn't for me or maybe i gave up too soon but i just did not enjoy that
[Guest] 我觉得那些模型还不够好。我觉得用自动补全的方式来用这些模型，而不是用 agent harnesses，真的很糟糕，很烦人。
I didn't think the models were good enough. I thought the way of using the models with autocomplete versus agent harnesses was just dreadful, annoying.
[Guest] 事实上，有那么一小会儿，我对整个行业的发展方向都有点悲观了，因为我以为这就是以后大家都要做的事：全都坐在那里，啪嗒啪嗒啪嗒地按键。
In fact, to the point that I got a little pessimistic about the direction of the industry for a hot second, because I thought this was what we were all going to do. We're all going to sit and do tap, tap, tap.
[Guest] 不了，谢谢。
No, thank you.
[Host] 对啊，Cursor 甚至——他们有个周边就是一个 Tap 键，
Well, Curse or even have they had even got one of these one of their swags was a tap key,
[Guest] 没错。
Exactly.
[Host] 那个感觉就很——我确实从他们那儿拿到过一个。东西做得很酷，设计也非常好看，各方面都很漂亮，但也很反乌托邦。
which which felt very and I haven't I got it from them. It's really cool, very well designed and all that beautiful design, but dystopian.
[Guest] 我一看到那个，就想起那阵子流行过的一个梗：我们其实只需要键盘上的三个字符，对吧？我就想到《The Simpsons》里有一集，Homer 在键盘上放了一只机械鸟。
When I see that, and I remember that was a meme for a while, just we only need three characters on the keyboard, right? I thought of that episode of The Simpsons where Homer puts a mechanical bird on the keyboard.
[Guest] 它就一路往下点，直接按回车，因为它之前做的事就只有按回车。结果突然跳出一个警告，说核反应堆核心要过载了，那只鸟还是直接按了回车，然后整个东西就烧毁了。我当时就想，哇，这个类比也太贴切了。《The Simpsons》还真是什么都能预测到。不过我不太喜欢那种用法，虽然我对整体发展方向还是一样很有热情，因为这东西确实太惊人了。
that just dips down and hits enter because all he's been doing is hit enter except suddenly there's a warning about the nuclear core overloading and the bird just hits enter and the whole thing burns down i'm like wow that's quite a parallel the simpsons really does predict everything but i did not like that style of using it as much as i retain my enthusiasm for the general direction of travel because it truly is amazing
[Guest] 而对我来说，这种惊艳感，我会尽量把它当成一种导师模型、一个不会替你开车的结对程序员来接受。有 ChatGPT 和其他模型在那里，真的很神奇。比如我会说，我没完全理解这个。这是一段代码。这是一个问题。
And the amazement to me, I try to embrace as a tutor model, as a peer programmer who doesn't drive. It was amazing to have chat GPT and the other models just be there for like, I don't understand this fully. Here's a piece of code. Here's a question.
[Guest] 你能告诉我它为什么会这样工作吗？你能告诉我它哪里有问题吗？因为从第一天起，我就是这么用互联网的，对吧？Google 对我来说就是干这个的。给你一条报错信息。给你一个概念。
Can you tell me why it works like that? Can you tell me what's wrong with it? Because that's how I've been using the Internet since day one, right? That's what Google was for me. Here's an error message. Here's our concept.
[Guest] 也许我会在 Stack Overflow 上找到点东西，上面有个带着点被动攻击味道的技术宅在那儿告诉所有人他有多聪明，然后在最底下才有我想要的解决方案；要么就是我根本找不到，那就挺让人沮丧的。
Maybe I find something on Stack Overflow with some passive aggressive nerd telling everyone why he's so smart and then at the bottom there's the solution I'm looking for or I don't find it at all and that's just kind of frustrating.
[Guest] 但用 ChatGPT 模型时，我经常能得到非常好的解释。
With the chat GPT model, I very often got a really good explanation.
[Host] 对，这个其实让我想到我之前和一位游戏开发者 Jonas Tyroller 聊过。他做了一款特别酷、而且卖得很好的游戏，我自己也很喜欢玩。当时正好是代码自动补全特别火的那段时间。
Yeah, this was actually I talked with a game developer Jonas Tyroller who built this really cool best-selling game I loved playing it and this was during this time of the top completion
[Host] 他说他的工作方式是，直接把 IDE 里所有自动补全都关掉，因为他被那玩意儿搞烦了。然后隔一阵子他才去 ChatGPT 那里问点问题，或者进行一段更长的交流。这样他的模式就变成了：我在思考，我在做这些事；哦，我需要一点帮助，好，那我就把具体情况给出来，再把结果拿回来。不知怎么的，这样一来感觉他一整天都处在心流里，因为主动权是他自己在控制。
completion and he said that in his the way he works is he just turned off all out of completions in his id because he got annoyed by it and then every now and then he went to chat gpt to ask something or have a longer thing and then he had the mode of like i'm thinking and i'm doing this stuff oh i need some help okay here's the specifics and i'm taking and somehow it felt that you know like he just he was in the zone the whole day by controlling it
[Guest] 对。
Yes,
[Host] 而且不知怎么的，那些习惯听起来就像是，你知道，你一直在重复同样的话，感觉有点把它原本的味道拿走了。
and and somehow those habits sounds like you know you're saying the same thing it kind of took it
[Guest] 没错。
exactly.
[Host] 让它离你、我们、我们、我们远了。
away from you us us us
[Guest] 对，而且我当时确实有点担心，那会不会变成我们大家都要走的方向，都要去当那只鸟，而我不想当那只鸟。然后我就想，那我该改做什么呢？也许去种土豆？这在 Denmark 这边也是很悠久的传统，也许我可以干这个。不过还好，后来——
exactly and i did get a little worried that that was going to be the direction that we were all going to be the bird and i didn't want to be the bird then i was like well what should i do instead maybe like farming potatoes like that's a long tradition here in denmark maybe i could take that up but then thankfully
[Host] 后来发生了两件事。第一，Cloud Code 在春天开始启动，到了夏天慢慢运转起来，等到秋天，靠用 agent harnesses 这种新方式让 agents 帮你写代码，已经开始有些起色了，对吧？
Two things happened. A, cloud code starts into spring, gets going sort of over the summer, then by the fall has some traction on a new way of using agents to help you code with the agent harnesses, right?
[Host] 也就是在这里，我们真正从 AI 过渡到了 agents。
This is really where we transition from AI to agents.
[Guest] 对。
Yes.
[Guest] AI 一下子就有了工具。它可以用 Bash，也可以调用你终端里现有的一切，还能在合适的时候连上互联网获取相关信息。
Suddenly the AI has tools. It can use Bash. It can use everything you got on your terminal. It can call the internet in for appropriate information.
[Guest] 它能做的不只是对你给它的某个东西，或者来自上下文文件输入的内容进行推理，然后再交给模型处理。
It just is capable of doing more than just reasoning about a thing you gave it or input from a source context file and then the models.
[Guest] 对我来说，Opus 4.5 是我们这条发展线上另一个关键节点——它是第一个会持续、稳定地用输出质量让我感到震惊的模型。
Opus 4.5 to me is the other one of the other points we're going to have on the line where it's the first model that continuously and consistently would shock me with the quality of its output.
[Guest] 它在面对模糊输入时的分析质量，以及更重要的，它输出结果的质量，都非常高。它写出来的代码，几乎不用改、甚至完全不用改，我就愿意直接 merge。
It quality of its analysis on the basis of vague inputs and even more importantly, the quality of its output. It produced code I wanted to merge without very much, if any,
[Guest] 而且如果我确实想改，我可以直接告诉它，它会记住，下次不会再犯同样的错。对我来说，这两点结合在一起，就是那个真正打开局面的关键。然后我——
alteration. And if I did want to do alteration, I could tell it and it would remember and it would not make the same mistake next time. That to me, the combination of those two things. was the unlock And i
[Host] 你的标准很高，
you have a high bar,
[Host] 就是你有个——
[Guest] 我的标准确实高得离谱。我们刚才已经详细聊过了，输出在美感上的表现对我来说真的很重要——如果我要看它、要审它的话。等下我再给你讲个例子，在那个场景里这些因素甚至都不重要。但当我用 agent 来处理 Ruby 代码时，我希望它们写出来的代码看起来跟我的一样好。如果它们写得很潦草，我是不会 merge 的，就像我也不会 merge 一个初级开发者写得很糙的代码一样。
like you have a
[Guest] 就是那种还没有完全内化我们风格之类要求的开发者，所以我希望它能达到同等水平、真正对齐，而早期的模型就是做不到。不过这并不意味着它们做不出能运行的软件。
have an incredibly high bar i as we've talked about now at length like the aesthetics of the output really matters if i'm gonna look at it and i'm gonna review it i'm gonna give you another anecdote in a second where those things don't even play in but when i'm using agents to work on ruby code i want their code to look as good as mine i'm not going to merge their stuff if it's sloppy no more than i would merge the work of a junior developer
[Guest] 至少有些时候它们是可以的，这已经非常惊人了。我的意思是，我记得我第一次做贪吃蛇游戏的时候，我心想，天哪，我从六岁起就一直想做这个。就是我脑子里有个点子，我想把它做成游戏，结果我居然能在，呃，不知道，短短三十秒内就看到它实现了，游戏代码都直接给出来了。
developer who has not yet fully internalized our style and so forth so i wanted to be on par and on parity and the early models just couldn't that didn't mean they couldn't produce working software
[Host] 太神奇了。
at least some of the time they could very impressive i mean i remember when i did my first snake game and i'm like holy smokes i've been wanting to do this since i was six years old like i've been wanting to i have this idea i want to get it into a game and i was able to see that in i don't know a few 30 seconds it was done with the game out copy
[Guest] 把 HTML 粘贴进去，
Magical
[Host] 当你
paste the html
[Guest] 太神奇了。
when
[Host] 第一次有这种
magical
[Guest] 体验，对吧。所以我觉得这种上手过程
you do your first
[Guest] 这件事很有意思，因为其实我们花了一段时间，才找到这种以终端界面为载体的 agent harness 形态。对我来说，那才是真正的关键突破点：从“这东西挺有意思”，变成“我也想跟它对话，我想让它帮我写代码”。现在我开始任何项目，基本都是先从 agent 开始。
experience right so i think that ramp
[Guest] 而这其实是个巨大的转变。我记得这大概就是从 11 月 27 号开始的，也就是 Opus 4.5 发布的时候。当然，也有人有不同看法，他们会觉得，哦，其实是从 Opus 4.0 开始，或者说可能是
was very interesting because it actually took a while until we found the form factor of the agent harness of the terminal interface that to me was the big unlock from this is interesting i want to have a conversation with it too i wanted to write my code i will now start any project i'm starting with i'm starting agent first
[Host] 还有 GPT
And that's a massive shift. And it just happened from November 27th, I believe, is when Opus 4.5 dropped. Now, there are other people who have different points. They felt like, oh, it's Opus 4.0 or maybe
[Host] 也有人在说
There's also GPT
[Host] -5
some people talk
[Host] 这个
-5
[Host] 也是。
about
[Guest] 还有 Sun 和 3.7。更早之前也有一些节点，但我确实觉得，大家大体上有个共识，Kpathy 和其他一些人也表达过类似看法：对，差不多就是在 11 月底、12 月初那个时间点。
too.
[Guest] 凡是在大一些科技公司工作过的人都知道，那会儿正好是寒假，因为大家基本上都会——
Sun and 3.7. There are other earlier checkpoints, but I do feel like there's a general consensus I can lean up against that Kpathy and others have expressed like, yep, it was right around end of November, early December.
[Host] 对。
Everyone who works. works worked at larger tech companies it was the winter break because people just you
[Guest] 你知道的，整个行业差不多都会停摆两周，除了少数需要值班 on call 的岗位，但总体来说，整个行业那段时间都不会做生产上的工作。
Yes.
[Host] 现在
know like like the whole industry shuts down for two weeks say for a few places where you're on call but again no production work happens across the
[Host] 整个行业
Now
[Host] 你就可以拿这个来玩了。
industry
[Guest] 我的感觉是，大家会拿它来玩，是因为你可以把自己的那些边角项目丢给它，反正你本来也没指望能做完，然后他们就——
you get to play with this.
[Host] 而且你还会——
my sense was that people were playing with it because you give it your side projects you're never finished expecting not to finish and then they
[Host] 搞定了。
also You're
[Host] 结束了。
got
[Guest] 震惊，对。
done.
[Host] 你完了。那完全就是一种——
shocked yeah
[Host] 像是突然断片了一样，对吧？如果这是部电影，你会听到那种刮盘声，然后你会想，等等，什么？倒回去，什么情况？
You're done. And that was just a complete.
[Host] 我
sort of break right like if this was a movie you'd hear the scratch sound like you're like wait what rewind what
[Host] 发生了什么
I
[Guest] 我觉得那是一种最集体性的震惊，只不过是每个人先各自经历了，然后大家到一月份又回来了。
happened
[Guest] 而且是所有人，尤其是很多决策者，比如 CTO、engineering director 之类的，以前其实没那么亲自动手，但这次他们真的上手了。很多人后来出现了一种很奇怪的情况：他们回去之后就开始强推，或者说，好，你们现在必须用这个，因为我已经看过未来了，我是真的亲手用过，你们也得去体验一下。所以这有点像又回到了硬件时代：人们会把新硬件直接塞到你手里，说你必须亲自感受一下。
feel it was the most collective shock which happened individually and then people came back in January.
[Host] 对。
and everyone especially because a lot of decision makers who are you know like cto's director of engineering etc were not as hands-on but they were hands-on and a lot of them it's this weird thing where they came back and they start to mandate or like say all right you guys need to use this because i've seen the future i've literally used it you need to see it so it's we're going back to a little bit of hardware like people were trying to give you know like the new hardware into people's hands saying you need to experience it
[Guest] 因为你不会轻易相信，对吧？这东西也有这种特点：你是真的很难相信。我们当然可以一直聊这个，但凡是没试过、或者还没经历那个“啊哈时刻”的人，我觉得我们是说服不了他们的。
Yes.
[Guest] 这又是那种光靠语言根本没用的情况。你得坐下来，打开 open code 或者你平时用的 whatever harness，直接上一个 frontier model，从这个开始，从 Opus 开始。我会说，就从 Opus 开始。
because you're you're not going to believe it right there's something with this as well where you really don't believe it we can talk about this and Then whoever's not tried or not had that aha moment. I don't think we can convince them
[Guest] 它是最好的 frontier model。其他模型在别的方面可能更强，诸如此类。但如果你只是想处理一段代码，想看看当前最前沿已经到什么程度了，而且如果你……如果你，
This is another one of those cases where words just are not effective. You need to sit down in front of open code or whatever harness that you use, use one of the frontier models, start with that, start with Opus. I'd say start with Opus.
[Guest] 我的意思是，如果你们的听众里居然还有人没试过，我会很震惊，但如果真还有那么几位的话，
It's the best frontier model. Other models are better at other things, blah, blah. But if you're just going to work on a piece of code and you want to see what the current frontier is, and if you... And if you,
[Guest] 现在就是时候了。而且我不希望有人被 X 上那股风气劝退，我真的很反感那种说法：好像除非你已经把 AI 的一切都彻底吃透了，不然你就已经掉队了。
I mean, I'd be shocked if any of your listeners haven't done it already, but if there should be some left,
[Guest] 少来。首先，这显然不是真的。你完全可以在接下来的三周里把这些都补起来。这也是这类项目，或者说这种进展，另一个神奇的地方，对吧？
now is the time. And I don't want anyone to say in the sense I found it really off-putting, this trend on X, where they go, unless you've internalized everything there is about AI, like you've been left behind.
[Guest] 如果我们是在去年春天聊这个，所有人都会说，MCP、MCP、MCP。不过你知道吗？现在你完全可以直接跳过那一整套，直接上 CLI 和 skills。
Shut up. First of all, patently not true. You could literally pick up everything. In the next three weeks. This is the other magical thing about this kind of project, right? Or progress.
[Guest] 这一点很值得记住：这种 FOMO，觉得如果你不能在事情发生的每一步都实时跟上，就会被甩下，这完全是胡扯。话虽这么说，我也还是承认，有些人确实看得更早，而对我来说，
When if we'd been having this conversation in spring of last year, everyone would have been like, MCPs, MCPs, MCPs. And you know what? You can now manage to just have jumped over that entire things and go straight to CLIs and skills.
[Guest] Shopify 的 toby lipkit 是最主要的那个人，他比我早得多就看到了这件事，也看到了它将带来的变化。他一直不断给我发消息，像是在说，嘿，你看看这个，看看这个，这真的把我一步步拉进来了。我确实觉得这很有帮助。身边有一些信念更强、或者说眼光看得更远一点的人，真的很有帮助——因为我的视线通常更贴近眼前这条路。
That's just worth having in mind that this FOMO, that unless you're up on all of it as it happens play by play, you're left behind is complete and other. Their nonsense that being said I can still appreciate that some people were early and for me
[Guest] 而有些人的目光会抬得更高一些，所以他们有时能看到一些东西，虽然不一定都会成真。但这一次，toby 两年前就准确看到了我们的方向。我直到去年 12 月，等这条路真正走到我面前时，才终于看清。而这很有意思，因为
toby lipkit at shopify is the main individual who saw this and saw the changes that were coming from it way earlier than i did and it really helped drag me into this by constantly sending me like hey you look at this look at this and i do think that's actually quite helpful it's quite helpful to be surrounded by people who have a higher faith or maybe their eyes are a little further up like my eyes tend to be
[Guest] 一路上我一直在说，对，等模型足够好了，等它们能做到这些事的时候，一切都会变得很惊艳。我当时还在想，哇，这可能还要 18 个月、两年，也许五年。要预测这种拐点真的非常难。我觉得连整个行业本身都没预测准这个拐点。你看，整个 Silicon Valley 以及周边地区、San Fran，都在全力推动这件事发生，
relatively close to the road right in front of me and some people have a gaze that's a little higher up and sometimes they see things that don't come to pass in this case toby saw exactly where we're going two years ago and i finally saw it because the road came to me in december and it's funny because
[Guest] 但要准确预测这条曲线什么时候开始像冰球杆那样陡然上扬，是非常困难的。不过后来它真的发生了。现在我的日常工作已经完全不一样了，我的——
along the way i kept saying like yep when the models get good enough when they can do all these things it's going to be amazing and thinking wow it's going to be i don't know 18 months two years maybe it's five years it's very hard to predict these infliction points and i think the industry itself didn't even predict the infliction point right you have an entire city silicon valley and surrounding areas san fran
[Host] 那你现在的日常工作是什么样的？
focused on making this happen but predicting exactly when the hockey stick starts hockeying is very difficult but then it happened and now my daily work is very different my
[Guest] 我的日常工作就是
So what is your daily work now?
[Guest] 凡事都要 agent first。
daily work is
[Host] 说到 agent first，正好可以提一下我们本季的赞助商 Sonar。转向 agent first 的工作方式时，一个必然会冒出来的问题就是代码质量。Sonar，也就是 SonarQube 的开发公司，
Agent first on everything.
[Host] 一直深信代码质量和代码安全本质上是紧密相连的。高质量的代码天然更有韧性，而当 agent 开始大规模编写代码时，
Going agent first is a good time to mention our season sponsor Sonar. When shifting to agent first work, one thing that inherently comes up is the quality of the code. Sonar, the makers of SonarQube,
[Host] 那一层验证就会成为你最重要的安全保障。安全参数。这时候，像 SonarQube advanced security 这样的解决方案就很有价值了。借助这项新的恶意软件包检测功能，
is deeply rooted in the core belief that code quality and code security are inherently linked. High quality code is naturally more resilient and as agents start writing code at a massive scale,
[Host] advanced security 提供了一个实时断路器，能在不可信或有风险的第三方库进入你的 pipeline 之前，自动阻止 agent 把它们拉进来。而且它带来的效果也是可量化的。
that verification layer becomes your most important security. Security parameter. This is where solutions like SonarQube advanced security are valuable. With this new malicious package detection,
[Host] 根据 Sonar 的《2026 代码开发者现状调查》报告，使用 Sonar 验证代码的开发者，因 AI 导致故障而上报问题的可能性要低 44%。
advanced security provides a real-time circuit breaker automatically stopping agents from pulling in unverified or risky third-party libraries before they ever hit your pipeline. The impact is measurable too.
[Host] 这其实就是在弥合 AI 的速度和生产环境安全现实之间的差距。Sonar 还在做哪些事，来帮助减少故障、提升安全性，并降低与 AI 和 agent 编码相关的风险？
Developers who verify their code with Sonar are 44% less likely to report experiencing outages due to AI as per Sonar's state of code developer survey 2026 report.
[Host] 去 sonarsource.com/Pragmatic 看看吧。说完这个，我们回到 David 的 agent-first 工作流。
It's really about closing the gap between the speed of AI and the reality of production security. What else is Sonar doing to help reduce outages, improve security, and lower risk associated with AI and agent decoding?
[Host] 具体来说，你用的是 Clothcloth code 还是
Head to sonarsource.com slash Pragmatic to find out. With this, let's get back to David's agent-first workflow.
[Guest] 我用
Does specifically Clothcloth code or
[Host] 是
I use
[Guest] open code
is
[Host] 是 open code，你用的是 open
open code
[Guest] 作为
it open code you use open
[Guest] code，对
as
[Guest] 我的主要工具。我也会稍微用一点 Claude code。很可惜，他们不幸抢到了先发优势。Opus 目前。
code yeah
[Guest] 成了最好的模型。于是他们的思路就有点变了，像是在把这场游戏当成一局定胜负，而不是多轮比赛来打。所以他们把订阅从 open code 里抽走了。这样一来，如果你想用你的 Mac 订阅，基本上就得用他们那套 harness。我不太喜欢这个做法，我觉得这是个错误。不过先把这个放一边，我们先庆祝一下他们确实有最好的模型，而且 open
my main harness. I also use Claude code a little bit. They unfortunately got that early lead. Opus is currently.
[Guest] 四、四五、四六也都不错，但对我来说，四五才是那个
the best model so then they started thinking a little bit in that like the game is single match instead of thinking it's multiple rounds and yank their subscription from open code so if you want to use your Mac subscription you kind of have to use their harness which I don't love it I think it's a mistake but leave that be for a second and let's just celebrate the fact that they have the best model and open
[Guest] 拐点，它带来了很多竞争，因为所有人都想追上，而且
is four four five four six is also nice but four five to me was the
[Guest] 他们还会
inflection point and it creates a lot of competition because everyone wants to catch up and
[Host] 超过他们
they'll of
[Guest] 当然，尤其是因为你看 Anthropic 的营收，我记得年初的时候是 90 亿，几周之后就到了差不多 140 亿，现在又到 190 亿之类的，简直是你能想象到最疯狂的火箭式增长，这也就
overtake them now
[Guest] 激励了大量资本投向竞争对手之类的方向，这很棒，很高兴看到。所以即便我不是喜欢他们做的每一件事，而且 cloud code 也不是我偏好的 harness，我还是会努力让自己脑子里同时装下两件事。我对 Apple 也是这样：我对他们的运作方式、他们充当 gatekeeper，还有我们聊过的其他那些乱七八糟的问题，确实有很多不满；但与此同时，我也会戴上那顶“我就是喜欢电脑”的帽子，然后说，我喜欢新的 Neo。
course and especially because you see anthropics revenues i think start of the year they're nine billion few years a few weeks later they're at like whatever 14 now they're 19 or something it's just the craziest rocket ship you could possibly imagine which is
[Guest] 我甚至可能会买一台新的 Neo，就想看看 500 美元这个价位能做到什么。至于 Opus，我用 Opus 完全没有顾虑。事实上，每当我觉得这是个特别难的问题时，我现在就会去用 Opus。但我也会用其他模型。
inspiring all this capital to be deployed for competitors and so forth which is wonderful great to see so even if i don't love everything that they do and cloud code is not my preferred harness manage to hold two things in your head at the same time this is what i also try to do even with apple which i have serious griefs about how they operate and act as the gatekeeper and all the other nonsense we've talked about and then i also keep my i just love computers hat on and go i like the new neo
[Guest] 我现在已经融入自己工作流的一件事，就是同时跑两个模型，而且速度还不一样。
I might even buy a new Neo and just see what is possible at $500. For Opus, I have no qualms about using Opus. In fact, whenever I feel like this is a really hard problem, I go to Opus right now. But I also use other models.
[Guest] 所以我会用 Tmux，我还有个内置在 Apache 里的布局功能，它会在左边启动我新的 Vim 编辑器，然后在右边开两个窗格。上面是 open code 跑 Timmy K25，下面是 Opus 在 cloud code 里跑，最底下还有一条终端栏，基本上我大多数操作都在这里完成。
And one of the things I've incorporated into my flow is to kind of have two models going at the same time. at different speeds.
[Guest] 我会先在其中一个 agent 里开始，告诉它我想要什么。然后我切到 NeoVim，先按一下 space GG 看它生成的 Git diff。只要改动看起来没问题，我就直接提交。搞定，很棒。
So I use Tmux and I have this layout thing that's built into Apache where it'll start my new Vim editor on the left side and then it'll start two panes on the right side. On the top is open code running Timmy K25 and on the bottom is Opus running in cloud code and then at the very bottom I have a strip of terminal and almost everything.
[Guest] 当然有时候看起来不对，我就会自己进去改代码。但这个比例，以及这个比例变化的速度，还是让人很震撼。从去年 11 月初开始，我原来一直都是先自己写代码再说。
I started in one of the agents and I tell them what I want. Then I hop over to NeoVim. First I do a space GG to look at the Lacey Git diff on it. Once this is changing, if it looks correct, I'll just commit. We're done. Great.
[Host] 对。
And then sometimes it doesn't look correct and I'll go in and alter the code myself. But the ratio and how quickly the ratio changes is still astounding. I went from early November last year. I'm code first everything.
[Guest] 我是先打开编辑器的。
Yeah.
[Guest] 我会自己先写，写多久都行。然后到了某个时候，如果我卡住了，或者想听听第二意见，我才会去问我那个友好的侧翼助手，给我一点第二意见。但现在已经完全不是这么回事了。现在我是先从 agent 开始。
I started the editor.
[Guest] 现在它会先给我一个草稿。我来审这个草稿，有需要的话再改一改。而且就在最近，我又把这个流程进一步倒过来了。
I'll spend whatever long it is. And then at some point, if I get stuck or if I want a second opinion, I'll go ask my friendly flanker to give me a second opinion. That's just not how it is anymore. Now I start with the agent.
[Guest] 所以我们在给 Basecamp 做一个 CLI，这样就能让 Basecamp 对 agent 完全可访问。真的很惊人。先等等，其实让我倒回去说一下。
Now it'll give me the draft. I'll review the draft and I'll make alterations if need be. And then just recently, I flipped it even further.
[Guest] 我一旦彻底意识到这些
So we're working on a CLI for Basecamp so we can get full agent accessibility for Basecamp. It's astounding. First, actually, let me rewind.
[Host] 对，我也是这么觉得。
As soon as I got pilled on how good the
[Guest] agent 有多厉害、能力有多强，我立刻就把视线拉到更远的终点去想：我们真的还需要 MCP 吗？真的还需要 CLI 吗？真的还需要任何东西吗？难道 agent 不能自己把这一切都搞定吗？
Hey, I felt.
[Guest] 那时候我装了 OpenClaw。于是我把 OpenClaw 装在一台 VM 上，然后我在想，我该拿它做点什么？来看看我们到底能把它推到多远，以及它能做到什么
agents were and how capable they were, I immediately tried to raise my gaze up towards the end of the road and think, do we even need MCP? Do we even need CLI? Do we even need anything? Can't the agent just figure it all out?
[Host] 削弱
This was when I installed OpenClaw. So I installed OpenClaw on a VM and I thought. What should I do here? Let's see how far we can push it and what
[Guest] 它能通过
Diminating
[Host] 前面
it can do by
[Guest] 本身。
front
[Host] 最后，嗯。
itself.
[Guest] 所以我就想，我想把这个 claw 放进 Basecamp，也想把这个 claw 放进 Fizzy。那我就试试看，像邀请一个真人那样邀请它。我就直接给它写：你能注册一下 Fizzy 吗？我不给你任何工具。
end, yeah.
[Guest] 我不给你任何 MCP，也不给你 CLI。我只是告诉你，网址是 fizzy.do。去注册吧。然后你就看着它一路跑下去，然后，嗯，
So I thought I want this claw in Basecamp. I want this claw in Fizzy. Let me just try to invite it as it was a human. So I just wrote it. Can you sign up for Fizzy? I'm not giving you any tools.
[Guest] 它说，我注册上了，但它在要一个邮箱地址，或者说，我正在注册，它在要一个邮箱地址。我就想，哦，对哦，你得有个邮箱地址，而 agent 又没有邮箱地址。那就，嘿，去注册个 HEY.com 吧。
I'm not giving you any MCP. I'm not giving you CLI. I'm just telling you it's at fizzy.do. Go sign up. And you see it chuck along and then yeah,
[Guest] 我心想，这次它肯定要失败了。结果它就咔咔咔一顿操作：我已经注册好了 HEY.com。这是密码，记得记在安全的地方。我现在也注册好了 Fizzy。确认邮件我已经收进收件箱了。
I'm signed up, but it's asking for an email address or I'm trying to sign up It's asking for an email address. I'm like, oh, yeah, right. You need an email address and agent doesn't have an email address Hey go sign up for hey calm.
[Guest] 一切都搞定了。你想让我接下来做什么？我当时就想，什么？你的意思是，你居然能一次搞定，通过浏览器把这些都注册好？当然，也许这本来就不算太让人惊讶。
I'm like it's gonna fail this one and it's Chuck Chuck Chuck. I signed up for hey calm. Here's the password write it down somewhere safe I'm now also signed up for busy. I got the confirmation email in my inbox.
[Guest] 也许用 Sonic 3 或者更早期的一些模型，这本来就已经能做到了，我也不确定。但当你亲自在自己那个该死的 claw 上体验到这件事——你只是通过 telegram 告诉它去做点什么，它居然就能自主去注册这些产品——那感觉还是完全不一样。
We're all good What do you want me to do? I'm like, what? Are you telling me that you could one shot signing up through a browser to these things? Now, maybe that shouldn't be surprising.
[Guest] 这挺让人震惊的。对我来说确实如此。然后下一次我就想，如果它能注册 Hey、给 Fizzy 做设计，那我也让它进 Basecamp 吧。所以我把邀请发到了它自己的邮箱地址。
Maybe that was already possible with Sonic 3 or one of the early models. I don't know. But when you experience it yourself on your own damn claw that you're just telling over telegram to do something and it's signing up for products autonomously.
[Guest] 这是 Basecamp 的邀请链接。你能直接进我们那个 AI Labs Lab 项目，然后跟团队做个自我介绍吗？
That's pretty startling. It was for me. And then the next time I went like, well, if they can sign up for Hey and design for Fizzy, let me invite it to Basecamp. So I sent it an invitation to its own email address.
[Guest] 嘿，我是 David 的助理。很高兴认识大家。我稍微回看了一下聊天记录，看得出来你们都对这些东西很兴奋，然后就继续聊起来了。
Here's the invitation link to Basecamp. Can you just jump into the AI Labs Lab project that we have and introduce yourself to the team?
[Guest] 就是，就是，那很有意思，因为这让我看到，即便这需要一点时间——而且确实花了点时间，在 agent 的语境里，大概花了，我不知道，七分钟——当时感觉像是永恒一样，但它确实是能做到的。
Hey, I'm David's assistant. It's very nice to meet you all. I've read back the transcript a little bit. I see you're all excited about these things and you just go again.
[Guest] 它是能把事情做成的，而这看起来就像最终形态。最终形态就是，agents 不需要我们做任何迁就，不需要任何上手引导。它们不是坐着什么小小的
what what and that was fun because it showed me that even if it was going to take a while it did take a while it took a while this is the agent terms it took i don't know seven minutes that was like oh it feels like eternity but it was
[Guest] 轮椅进场，它们会踩着仿生腿进来，然后在大概两秒钟内跑得比你快五倍。这个速度问题我们等会儿再说。但你也会意识到，好吧，
Something to do it and that seems like the end state the end state is that agents will not need any of our accommodations They do not need any on-ramp. They're not coming on a little
[Guest] 我不能只是坐在那里干等 AGI 发生。我们得为当下去构建。这也是我们一直在为 Basecamp 做的事。我们已经在做 CLI 了。我们也会给 Hey 做，也会给 Fizzy 做。
Wheelchair they'll be coming on bionic legs and running five times as fast as you in about two seconds Which we'll get to in a second to the speed aspect of it But then you also realize, okay, well,
[Guest] 我们会把它做进所有产品里，甚至可能包括一些老产品。我对 CLI 特别喜欢的一点——就像我也很喜欢这些 harnesses 一样——是它们验证了那个大概从 71 年就有的 Unix 基本哲学。
I can't just sit around fiddling my thumbs until AGI happens. Let's build for today. And that's what we've been building for Basecamp. We've been building CLI. We're going to build it for Hey. We're going to build it for Fizzy.
[Guest] 你就应该构建一些能互相协作的小工具。可以通过管道来配合运行，你也可以
We're going to build it for everything, even probably some of the legacy products. And what I love about the CLIs, as much as I also love it about these harnesses, is that they validated the fundamental Unix philosophy from like whatever, 71.
[Host] 这就
You should just build small tools that can interoperate. to operate with pipes and you can
[Host] 把
That's
[Host] Unix
put
[Host] 那套哲学串起来了。
the Unix
[Host] 对吧？
things philosophy, together.
[Guest] 就是
right?
[Host] 对。
It's
[Guest] 这完全就是 Unix 哲学。
Yeah.
[Guest] 而这对我来说，真正神奇的地方就在于看到所有东西都有 CLI。不是说 Basecamp 现在因为有了 CLI 就更好用了。不是，不是。重点是 GitHub 也有 CLI，Sentry 也是。我不知道他们有没有 CLI，但他们有 MCP。这样你就能把这些东西全都串起来，然后你就可以对一个 agent 说，
the total Unix philosophy.
[Guest] 嘿，Sentry 里有一些报错。你能去看一下吗？然后把总结发到 Basecamp。
And that is actually the magic to me about seeing everything having a CLI. It's not that Basecamp is easier to use now with the CLI. No, no. It's that GitHub also has a CLI and Sentry. I don't know if they have a CLI, but they have an MCP. That you can tie all these things together and now you can tell an agent,
[Guest] 一边梳理到底哪里出了问题，然后去 GitHub 提一个 pull request，做完之后再回到 Basecamp 留个评论。这样一来，我们就在 Basecamp 里有了一份中心化的记录，可以在工作进行的同时持续跟进，而 agent 则在那边干活、查资料。而且再说一次，当我们试着去描述这件事、把它转述出来的时候，
hey, we have some errors in Sentry. Can you go check them out? Then post a write-up to Basecamp.
[Guest] 我觉得有些人可能已经能看出来了，而且现在 YouTube 之类的平台上也已经有足够多 OpenClaw 的视频，所以你至少能搭个便车感受一下。但你要是亲自拿自己的产品、自己的任务、自己的 prompts 去试，你就会彻底入坑。
iterating what's wrong then go in github come up with a pull request post a comment back to base camp when you're done and now we have a central record in base camp where we're following the work as it's going on while we have an agent doing work looking things up and again when we try to talk about it and relay it
[Guest] 你会一边对我们竟然能让沙子——也就是硅、芯片、权重参数，整套这一切——做到这种程度而感到无比兴奋。
I guess some people can see it, and now OpenClaw has enough videos on YouTube and so forth so you can get at least a passenger ride. But try it yourself with your own product, with your own tasks, and with your own prompts, and you will be pilled.
[Guest] 哦，而且同时你也会有一点焦虑，担心这一切最终会走向哪里。也正是在这种张力里，我，还有大概所有真正被这东西震到的人，都会当场想：等等，如果我们现在都已经到这一步了，那 18 个月之后会是什么样？
You will be simultaneously incredibly excited for what we've been able to make sand do, the silicon, the chips, the weights, the whole thing.
[Guest] 如果说就在过去三个月里，它已经彻底颠覆了我对计算机能力边界的理解，那接下来的三个月会是什么样？接下来的九个月又会是什么样？
oh and and also a little bit anxious about where it's all going to go and it's in that tension that i and probably anyone else who's been pilled on this live right wait a minute if we're already here What does 18 months from now look like?
[Host] 对，
Like if in the last three months we've upended my entire understanding of what's possible with computers, what does the next three months look like? What does the next nine months look
[Host] 比如说？
Yeah,
[Host] 这点上我以前很长一段时间都比较站你这边，我觉得现在可能还是这样：我相信真正有效的东西，而且我一直对各种预测持怀疑态度。
like?
[Host] Moore's law 在某个时候失效了。我经历过那个人人都说它会永远持续下去的阶段，你懂的，后来它还是像我们大家怀疑的那样，失效了。
this is where like I was a little bit on your end for a long time and I think I still am where I believe what works and I'm always skeptical of projections.
[Host] 但是
Moore's law broke down at some point. I lived through everyone said it will continue forever and you know and then it broke as we all suspected it would.
but
[Host] 然后
[Host] 并不是
then
[Host] 去找到
not
[Guest] 对
to find
[Guest] 还有一种角度，我觉得你提到 Moore's law 这点很好，对吧。它在单个核心层面上已经失效了，你还能把它推到多高呢？然后我们就转而想，那如果你直接堆更多核心呢？现在最新的芯片是什么，AMD Zen 芯片都到 256 了，对吧。
yes
[Guest] 而且即便性能提升这条路走不动了，我们又转向了功耗、尺寸，以及所有这些别的维度。所以是啊，但我也很难直接说，哦，它会停在这里，因为我们已经看到它一直在增长，我们也知道他们在采用哪些方法：更大、越来越大的
another way i think it's a good point about the moore's law right it broke for individual course how much can you push it and then we just went well what if you just had what's the latest chip 256 on the amd zen chips right
[Guest] 更大的训练集，而且到目前为止一直都有效。还有那个 bitter lesson，我觉得那真是一篇特别值得读的短文，篇幅很短，但非常值得一读。我觉得它可能是学术圈外最受欢迎的论文之一，因为
and even when performance broke we we went into power consumption and size and all of those things so yeah like but it's it's harder for me to also just to say oh it's going to stop here because we've seen it grow we we know the approaches that they're taking this is larger and larger
[Host] 对。
larger training sets and it's been working so far and there's also the bitter lesson which i think i think is a it's such a short paper that it's just so worth reading i think it's one of probably the most popular papers outside of academic circles because
[Guest] 它就是把这样一件事讲透了：我们不愿意相信，我们总想相信自己的知识、自己的理解更高明；好像你我会写代码，或者我投入了这 15 年，不管具体多少年，这些东西是很特别的。但有时候现实会告诉你，它也没那么特别。
Yes.
[Host] 有意思的是，其实就在此时此刻，从这个时间切片来看，它多少还真是这样。这会带来一个很有意思的验证过程：初级开发者和资深开发者之间的差别。
it just plays out this thing that we don't want to believe that we want to believe that our knowledge our understanding is superior that you know you and me knowing how to code or me putting in these 15 years or however long it's been it's special sometimes it shows that it's not as special
[Host] 我在 Third Time Signal 看到过最成功、也最适用的 agent 加速，往往都来自最资深的那些人。
What's interesting, actually, is like right this second, this snapshot in time, it a little bit is. And this is a funny verification that's happening, junior versus senior developer,
[Host] 就是那些能够判断 agent 产出的东西，是否适合部署给几百万用户的人。昨天刚有个新闻，说 Amazon 出现了一些重大故障，
is that the most successful and applicable agent acceleration that I've seen at third time signal has been from the most senior people,
[Guest] 对。
the people who are able to validate whether what the agent produces is suitable to be deployed to millions of people. There was just this story yesterday about some of the major outages at Amazon and
[Host] 而 Amazon 自己的内部分析基本上把原因归结为：我们不能再让初级程序员在没有审核的情况下，把 agent 生成的代码直接发到生产环境了。问题就在于——
Yep.
[Guest] 首先，我觉得这就是现在整个行业里大多数公司都在意识到的一点。只要是那种任务关键型、性质类似的事情，我们目前还不能依赖 agent 去协助处理，
Amazon's own internal analysis essentially pinned that we can no longer let junior programmers ship agent generated code to production without review. And the problem with that is.
[Guest] 而初级程序员又没有能力把这个问题判断清楚。所以，他们的角色一下子就变得比以前更不稳了。
First of all, I think that's the realization most companies are now having across the industry. Whenever it's mission critical for something of that nature, we cannot yet rely on the agents to abet it at all,
[Guest] 跟六到九个月前相比更是如此，因为资深程序员可以做到，这也是为什么资深程序员现在获得了大得多的加速，他们——
and junior programmers are not capable of figuring it out. Therefore, their role is suddenly more tenuous than it was.
[Host] 对。
six nine months ago because a senior programmer can and this is why senior programmers are getting so much more acceleration they're
[Guest] 首先，他们能够和大量 agent 并行协作，但关键在于要审慎评估 agent 输出的质量，并且高度确信这东西到底能不能行；如果不行，还要能及时把它们导回正确方向，因为这
Yep.
[Guest] 这本来就是他们之所以能成为资深人员的原因。这原本就是他们承担的角色：他们有长期的内部经验、历史积累，以及对整体架构的全局视角。所有东西是怎么拼在一起的？这能行吗？这不行吗？
able to first of all work in parallel with lots of agents but critically examine the quality of the agent output and have a high degree of confidence of whether this is going to work or not or redirect them if not because this
[Guest] 这就是他们过去面对初级程序员时所扮演的角色。但现在，他们可以把这个角色用在 agent 身上。而且 agent 在执行指令和接受纠偏方面速度更快。于是突然之间，你就有了……
This is what made them senior in the first place. This was the role that they had, that they had the long inside and history and overview of the architecture. How does it all fit in? Is this going to work? Is this not going to work?
[Guest] 资深开发者可以把个人生产力提升到 5 倍、10 倍。而这还会带来第二层效应：如果你真的把一个资深开发者提升了 5 倍或 10 倍，那这个人每小时的价值也就直接涨了 10 倍。现在再想想，如果把这一个小时，不是让这个人花在和 agent 一起持续交付东西、把事情做得更好上，而是像以前那样把这一个小时花在
This was the role they played to junior programmers. But now they can play that role to agents. And agents are faster at following instructions and redirections. And suddenly you have...
[Guest] 教一个初级的人类员工怎么把事情做得更好。现在这个等式里有些东西正在发生作用，但最终会怎么演变，还不清楚。
senior developers who can 5x 10x their individual productivity and now this is the second order effect if you manage to 5x or 10x a senior developer that person's value per hour just went up 10x now take that hour instead of that person spending it with the agents just shipping stuff and making things better they spend that hour as they would before
[Guest] 一种可能的演变方式是，agent 会变得非常强，以至于它们不再犯错。它们会在交付可运行代码这件事上，具备资深工程师的能力。
Teaching a junior human how to do things better. There's something in that equation that's in play right now, and it's not clear how it's going to map out.
[Guest] 如果把时间往后推一段来看，这会是我的判断，因为汽车领域刚刚就发生了类似的事。所以现在自动驾驶的 Tesla，开车已经比人类更好了。不是比所有人都强，也不是在所有场景下都更强，但平均来看是这样。
One way it could map out is that the agents will get so good that they stop making mistakes. They become senior in their capacity to ship working code.
[Guest] 如果我们能够把这种会带来致命风险、也是我们日常面对的最高关键级别风险委托出去，这种情况是完全有可能发生的。
This is what my bet would be if we look X amount of time forward, because this is what just happened with cars. So self-driving Teslas now drive better than humans do. Not all humans, not in all circumstances, but on average.
[Guest] 就像我们现在坐在一个金属管子里，旁边还有别的金属管子，以每小时 60 英里的速度跑着，随便谁犯个错都可能出事，但我们还是把这事交给一个代理来处理。那它大概也能想办法把代码跑通，对吧？所以我确实觉得这会到来，但谁知道是什么时候、会怎么来呢？现在这个阶段，大部分收益还是落在最资深的开发者身上。
It's very possible that if we're able to delegate the mortal risk, the highest criticality we basically deal with on a daily basis.
[Host] 而且我也在想，这就像自动驾驶一样，你会发现永远都有各种前提和限制。比如说。
this sitting in a metal tube along other metal tubes that go 60 miles an hour where you can dive someone makes a mistake we delegate that to an agent well they can probably figure out how to make the code work too right so i do think it's coming but who knows when who knows how right now we're at a stage where the bulk of the benefits are accruing to the most senior developers
[Host] 在公司内部，这些事就很重要。你要是个 startup，零客户，那无所谓，你一次生成完就行，就算不能用、就算崩了也没关系。但在这些公司内部，像 Uber，我刚了解到他们是怎么采用 AI 的，他们有各种工具、cloud code 之类的一堆东西。但你会发现，真把它放进去之后，问题就来了：他们有各种内部 monorepo，有工单系统，有 slog，还有一大堆东西；他们有 RFC、设计文档，记录他们是怎么做、为什么这么做的。总之就是一团乱麻。
And also, I wonder, just like with self-driving, like you realize there's always caveats. So, for example.
[Host] 还有 microservices——这也是我们很多很多年前最早建立联系的一个有意思的话题——但他们后来发现，自己搭了很多内部系统，其中很大一部分是为了帮助、喂给这些实体、agent harnesses 之类的东西。现在这些系统确实开始更好用了。但你也知道，我们现在所处的阶段就是这样。这也是为什么，如果你是在这类公司里的资深工程师，或者像 Uber 这样的 staff engineer，你跳去 Google 之后，一开始不会像原来那么有价值、也不会那么高效，得先把所有这些系统学会才行。
inside companies where it matters when you're a startup you have zero customers it doesn't matter you can one shot it and it doesn't matter if it doesn't work and you know it crashes but inside these companies uh at uber um just got details on how they're adopting ai and and they have all these tools cloud code and all these things but what you realize is well when you just put it in there they have all these internal monorepos they have their ticketing systems they have their slog they have so much they have their rfcs design documents on on how and why they have this jumble of a mess uh
[Host] 所以我只是
with microservices which which was a fun way that we originally connected like many many years ago but what they found is they built a bunch of internal systems a lot of it to help to feed entities agent harnesses and now they're working better but you know this where we are right now is there's and this is why if you're senior engineer in one of these companies or a staff engineer at like uber and you move to google suddenly you're not going to be as valuable or as efficient for a while until you learn all the systems
[Guest] 对。
So All I
[Host] 我就在想，会不会也像自动驾驶一样。你知道，自动驾驶其实已经很好用了。我之前在 SF 和 LA，Waymo 开得特别稳、特别舒服。就是，嗯，
right.
[Guest] 我的 Teslas 在 LA 也一直在开，每次都载我们全家去机场。整个路程我都很放松地坐着，看着路，但完全不用自己打方向盘。
wonder if just like with self-driving, you know, self-driving works great as well. I was in SF and in LA and Waymo's drive so nice. Like, well,
[Host] 除外。
My Teslas are driving in LA, driving us to the airport every time, the whole family. I sit peacefully, watch the road, but do not steer at all on that entire journey.
[Host] 我的 Waymo 有一次卡住了，因为一辆卡车在一条狭窄的街上停车，旁边还有辆车边上有个自行车棚。我当时就知道它其实不该往那儿开，但它自己不知道，所以后来有人类操作员介入了。不过话说回来，就算是 Waymo 也是这样，你知道的，会有这些情况。比如它们通常是在天气不错的时候开，而且路线都是提前测绘过的。所以我就在想，在软件工程里是不是也有类似的平行之处：这些公司都有自己很特殊、很专门化的环境，一旦你把它
except.
[Host] 测绘清楚了，把工具都做好了，把这些问题都摸透了——而且自动驾驶也是花了 10 年，对吧？我当时在 Uber，他们收购自动驾驶业务的时候，新闻里都在说，你知道，明年司机这个职业就要完了，结果根本没有。
my my waymo got stuck because a truck was parking on on a narrow street and a car had a bike shed and i i i knew that it should i should not go there but it didn't know so human operator came in but anyway but even with waymo's you know like there's there's things like there's they drive in pretty good weather they've been mapped out so i wonder if in software engineering i wonder if this has these parallels where we have all of you know like these companies have their their special lot specialized landscape and once you map
[Guest] 对，说以后连方向盘都不会有了。顺便说一句，这其实是个很惊人的轶事，因为它恰恰说明了 Elon 对自己使命的那种。
map it once you do all the tools once you figure out these things and with self-driving it took it took 10 years right like i was at uber when they bought the self-driving thing and we were hearing in the news that you know next year it's all going to be over for drivers and no
[Guest] 绝对信念，因为在 17 年他做出那个宣告的时候，那套 AI 其实还是 50 万行手写的 C++ 代码，就像——
Yes, there are not going to be steering wheels anymore, which, by the way, is an amazing anecdote because it just shows Elon's.
[Host] 对。
total faith in his mission because in 17 when he made that proclamation it was an ai it was 500 000 lines of hand-coded c++ like
[Guest] 那个模型根本、永远都不可能把我们带到完全自动驾驶。但他就是对那个愿景有着绝对的信心。然后最终，AI 真的来了，而且强得惊人。如果你用数十亿小时的道路驾驶数据去训练它，它实际上真的能做到，而且事实上它比大多数人类开得都更好。我算是——
Right.
[Guest] 一个挺不错的司机，我想这么说。
that model was never ever going to get us to the full self-driving but he had just total faith in the vision and then eventually hey here along comes ai and it's so good and if you train it on billions of hours of road use it actually can do it and it can do it better than most humans in fact i'm
[Guest] 我不是最好的司机，因为我这人吧，不知道算不算没耐心，老是忍不住踩油门。对我来说是挺爽，但对乘客来说就不一定舒服了。可一旦让我开 Tesla 的 autopilot，
A pretty good driver, I'd like to say.
[Guest] 那简直就是世界上最好的司机。就是完美地
I'm not the best chauffeur because my, I don't know, impatience have a tendency to provoke the throttle that's not always as pleasant for passengers as it is fun for me. And when I let the Tesla autopilot drive,
[Host] 比
it's just the best chauffeur in the world. It's just perfectly
[Guest] 冷静。
Better
[Host] 你还强。
calm.
[Guest] 比我强。比女王的司机都强，我觉得。它的油门控制和减速表现，
than you.
[Guest] 简直神了。在那个狭窄领域里的应用上，它实际上已经有点像 AGI，甚至像 ASI 了。当然，当我们看到这些案例、这些例子时，会觉得“我的天”，不仅自动驾驶并不是花了 10 年才做到，而是从当初放出豪言到现在过了 10 年；而且其中有 7 年，他们做的东西跟现在 FSD 在做的根本不是一回事，因为现在这个基于 AI 的 FSD
Better than me. Better than the queen's chauffeur, I think. Like it's throttle actuation and deceleration.
[Guest] 其实运行的时间并没有那么久。但到了那个拐点，我记得应该是 FSD 13.1，FSD 13.1 刚出来的时候，你会觉得，哇，这已经相当不错了，不过我最好还是盯紧点。到了 13.2、14.0、14.2，在 18 个月里，我们从“嗯，挺不错，但我还是得注意着点”，变成了“那方向盘为什么还在那儿”，以及那种加速表现，在那么短的时间里你就
is godlike it's actually agi like or asi like in its application within that narrow domain and of course when we get these anecdotes and these examples of holy smokes not only it didn't take 10 years for the self-driving it took 10 years from the proclamation but what they were doing for seven of those years had nothing to do with what they're doing with fsd now because the fsd that's based on ai
[Host] 当然了，一说到编程，大家都会拿这个来说，然后觉得，嗯，
hadn't been running for that long but the infliction point of i think it was 13-1 fsd 13-1 like the first version you're like wow this is pretty good but like i better pay attention 13-2 14-0 14-2 over the course of 18 months we went from yeah that's pretty good but like i'm gonna pay attention here to why is there a steering wheel and that acceleration that short period of time you
[Host] 如果我们现在已经到了这个阶段，而资深程序员还是得去审查它，不然的话，AWS 那边就会因为某个 AI 推出了一堆胡来东西，搞出什么四级、八级严重故障停机之类的问题，
Of course, it's something people look to when it comes to programming and go like, well,
[Guest] 那如果它像 FSD 一样，在同样一段时间里再往前跃升一步，会变成什么样？不过我也觉得，你要是整天坐在那里拼命吸收这些信息，很容易把自己搞疯。这也是我过去一年试过的做法。就是，
if we're here now and senior programmers still have to review it because otherwise you're going to get all your whatever four severity eight downtimes at AWS because some AI pushed out some nonsense,
[Guest] 我对这东西未来会走到哪里真的很兴奋。但我也会先面对今天能做到什么、今天什么是有意思的，以及我们现在到底在做什么。
what is it going to look like when they take the jump that FSD did over the same period of time? Now, I also think you can go completely crazy trying to just sit and soak in all of that. This is what I tried to do over the past year. Go,
[Guest] 我不会试图去规划 12 个月后我的人生会是什么样，毕竟到时候也许我们已经有 AGI 了，也许还没有。当然，也有些人特别擅长做这个。我刚看了去年 Leopold 在 Dworkesh 节目上的一次采访。
I'm really excited for where this is going. But I'm also going to deal with what's possible today and what's enjoyable today and what we do right now.
[Guest] 他思考的是，2030 年会是什么样？那种 10 吉瓦的数据中心会是什么样？我就会想，还好有这样的人愿意去认真琢磨这些，因为那不是我最喜欢待的位置。
I'm not going to try to plan what my life looks like 12 months from now when maybe we do have AGI or we don't. Now, there are other people who do that very well. I just watched an interview with Leopold on Dworkesh from last year.
[Guest] 而且我觉得，大多数人其实也没那么擅长打磨自己的水晶球。
He's thinking like, what does 2030 look like? What does the whatever 10 gigawatt data center look like? I'm like, I'm very glad we have individuals who put thought into that because that's not my.
[Host] 对，我是说，作为软件工程师，这多少有点让人不安。因为很明显，这就是整个行业想去的方向，这也是接下来会投入大量精力的地方。会有很多软件公司围绕这个建立起来，顺便说一句，这里面也已经融了很多 VC 的钱。这些公司会去攻这个方向，要么成功，要么死掉，公司的运作就是这样。但就今天你看到的情况来说，
favorite spot to be, and I think most people are not that good at polishing the crystal ball.
[Host] 不过在 37signals，软件工程师这边当然大多还是资深工程师，虽然你们也招了初级工程师。他们这类工作的变化是什么？他们对工作的满意度又有什么变化？因为这也是个问题，对吧，我们一直在争论这个。
no well i mean this is a little bit unsettling as a software engineer in the sense of like clearly this is where the industry wants to go this is where a lot of effort will be put there will be a lot of businesses software businesses built on there's a lot of vc money raised on this by the way who are going to tackle this and they will either like succeed or die that's what that's what the companies do but today what you see
[Guest] 对，是的。
yet at 37 signals uh with software engineers you of course have most experienced engineers although you did hire junior engineers as well how is their kind of work changing how is their satisfaction with with work because that's also a thing right we keep arguing about
[Host] 这些东西会不会让我们更痛苦？这是不是我们真正想做的事？对你来说又发生了什么变化？我觉得这点很关键。
like Yes.
[Guest] 这其实是最大的发现。甚至比这些 agent 的能力更重要的，是我自己在使用它们时的乐趣。去年夏天我上 Lex 那次采访的时候，我还在说，你知道吗，我不想当 agent 的项目经理，因为——
is it making us more miserable at these things is it what we want to do and how is it changing for you right i think it's
[Host] 对。
That's the biggest revelation, actually. More than even the capacity of the agents is my enjoyment running them. when I was on that Lex interview last summer, I was talking about, you know what, I don't want to be a project manager for agents because
[Guest] 因为我脑子里想的是“管理人的项目经理”那种模型。我觉得那不是我喜欢的工作。我不想离实际产出那么远。我想在一线，我想亲手写代码。
Yeah
[Guest] 我当时没意识到的是，管理一群 agent 的感觉，不太像是在当 agent 的项目经理，反而更像是——
I had the mental model of a project manager of humans. And I felt like that's not what I enjoy. I don't want to be that far away from the production. I want to be in the mix. I want to have my hands in the code.
[Guest] 像是钻进了一套超级机甲里，突然之间我不只有两只手，而是有了 12 只手；我可以同时盯着七个屏幕，操作五把键盘。事情依然是我在做，哪怕我不是把这些内容当作程序里的关键字亲手敲进去。我作为程序员被极大加速了。这是一种不同类型的程序员，但它依然保留着那种对美感的追求，至少在我产出 Ruby 代码的时候是这样，而且我还能把这点结合起来，同时还能——
What I failed to realize at the time was that running a bunch of agents feels less like being a project manager for agents and more like.
[Guest] 在一堆事情上效率高了太多，而且甚至连评估问题的能力都像是大脑被大幅升级了一样。我有一个特别震撼的时刻，是在 omachi 3.4 发布之前。我进了 GitHub，当时我们有，我也不知道，大概 250 个 PR 还在 pending，我就有点叹气，心想 250 个 PR，如果我每个花
like stepping into this super mech suit where suddenly i don't just have two arms i have 12 and i can now look at seven screens at the same time running five keyboards i'm still the one doing it even if i'm not typing this as a keyword in a program i have been hyper accelerated as a programmer it's a different kind of programmer but it still has the same affinity to aesthetics at least when i'm producing ruby code and i'm able to combine that while being
[Guest] 我也不知道，15 分钟看一个 PR，那我要多久才能全看完？然后我想，你知道吗？我试点别的办法吧。我就试着让 Claude 来处理，我甚至都没用什么 system prompt。
being vastly more productive on a bunch of things it's also like getting an incredible brain upgrade on even assessing issues one of the pilling moments i had was before the release of omachi 3.4 i went into github and we had i don't know 250 prs pending and i kind of just sighed a little bit and like 250 prs if i spend
[Guest] 我就是直接写 review URL，然后那个 URL 就是对应的 issue。
I don't know, 15 minutes on each PR. Like, how long is it going to take before I get to the end of it? And I thought, do you know what? Let me try something else. Let me just try to ask Claude to, I'm not even doing anything with the system.
[Host] 对。
I just do review URL and the URL is the issue.
[Host] 或者说是 PR。太夸张了。
Yeah.
[Guest] 我记得是 90 分钟里，我处理了 100 个 PR。而且也不是说我把它们全都 merge 了。事实上，我会说真正原样 merge 的只占很小一部分，可能 10%。然后大概还有 20% 被 merge 了，但用的是 Claude 的实现。
Or is the PR. I'm shocked.
[Guest] 程序员确实正确识别出了一个问题，但他是手写了一些代码，而我能看出来我
In 90 minutes, I think it was, I processed 100 PRs. And it wasn't that I merged all of them. In fact, I'd say I merged a small minority, maybe 10% got merged as is. Then maybe 20% got merged, but with clods implementation.
[Host] 那个
The programmer had correctly identified an issue, but hand rolled some code that I could see I
[Host] 不想要
That
[Host] 他们本来应该
didn't want
[Host] 保留的。
they should,
[Host] 对。
to keep.
[Guest] 或者有时候我甚至都看不出来。我就直接去问 Claude，它会说，大概是这里不太对。然后我就继续问 Claude：你能不能把这块从头重写一下？问题是对的，我们来修，但要用正确的方式修。它马上就能搞定。
yeah.
[Guest] 而且风格跟我写 Amachi 其余部分时几乎一模一样。当然，这不是什么特别高深的代码，基本上就是 bash 代码，
Or sometimes I couldn't even see it. I just asked Claude and they said like, it's not quite right. And then I just asked Claude. Can you just clean room this? This is the right problem. Let's fix it, but let's do it right. It would do it right away.
[Guest] 但 bash 代码也还是有它自己的形态，你会希望它长什么样，和整个项目的其余部分放在一起时是不是协调一致。在这个场景下，Agents opus 基本上一下就能拿捏住。
In exactly the style as I would have written the rest of Amachi. Now, this isn't the high code of something. It's mostly just bash code,
[Guest] 然后另一半里，大概有 25% 是那种我后来才意识到，其实我根本不想要这个，我们就不该有它；还有 25% 是 Claude 告诉我，也许这里是有点东西，但这个实现真的不太行。
but there's still a shape to bash code and how you want it to look and can it feel coherent with the rest of the project. Agents opus in this case would just nail it.
[Guest] 我们根本没法一路顺畅地把它做得很好。90 分钟里冒出上百个问题，我当时就往后一靠，心想，这要是我自己做，不得干上一整周？至少也得好几天吧？这到底什么情况？而且更夸张的是，
And then the second half of it was split between 25% things I didn't just realize I just don't want this, we shouldn't have it, and 25% Claude telling me maybe there's something here but it's really not a good implementation,
[Guest] Claude 对至少一半问题的分析，涉及的都是我完全不了解的东西。它显然是个比我能想象到的自己还要更聪明、更厉害的 reviewer、programmer？不过
we don't have a straight shot to making a great one. A hundred issues in 90 minutes and I sat back, this would have been a week's worth of work? Days at the very least? What the heck? And even more than that,
[Guest] 嗯，也不是说我连想都不敢想成为那样的人
Claude's analysis of at least half the issues pertained to things I knew nothing about. Where it was undeniably a smarter, better reviewer, programmer? that i could ever dream to be but
[Guest] 但那一刻我并没有
Well not dream to be
[Host] 但你本来也不会投入那么多
wasn't that moment i
[Host] 会
But you would have not put in the
[Host] 精力
would
[Host] 吧
effort
[Host] 为了
not
[Host] 已经做过了
for
[Guest] 那些
have done it
[Guest] 这就是为什么
those
[Guest] 领域
this was why
[Guest] 很多情况下，PR 一开始就是卡在这里的
areas
[Guest] 因为
the pr sat in the first place in many cases
[Guest] 我
Because
[Guest] 你
i
[Guest] 会看着
you
[Guest] 就知道，因为
would look
[Guest] 它然后说
knew it because
[Guest] 你
at it and go
[Guest] 就像
you
[Guest] 知道
like
[Guest] 我
knew
[Guest] 就是
i
[Guest] 觉得这里面是有点东西的，但接下来我还得去研究这个 debus 的东西，我得搞清楚这是不是正确的做法。我不想随便 merge 一个东西，结果后面又冒出别的问题。要做到这一点，agent accelerated
that
[Guest] 算是我编程生涯里前 20 的高光时刻之一，没错
think there's something here but like then i now have to read up on this debus thing i have to figure out is this the right way of doing it i don't want to just merge something that then has other issues and to be able to do that agent accelerated
[Host] 我喜欢你用 agent accelerated 这个说法，听起来它对那种卡在你这里、等你处理的工作特别高效。
was one of top 20 programming moments yes
[Host] 就是那种你不太想做，或者你也没那么擅长做的事，但要委派出去又很麻烦，因为说到底，你也是有团队的，对吧？
I like how you put agent accelerated and it sounds like it's especially efficient for work that is waiting on you,
[Host] 比如你当时大概没委派出去，是因为你知道那样并不会让事情更快或者做得更好。所以我就在想，AI 里是不是有这样一部分价值，因为我们经常会聊到，就是你知道的，那种——
but you don't want to do it or you're not as skilled of doing it, but it's a hassle to delegate because, again, like you have a team, right?
[Host] 公司，尤其是大公司，很喜欢衡量效率、PR 数这些指标，他们想看到影响力。但还有一种影响，是那些如果没有它我们以前根本不会去做的工作。
Like you but you probably didn't delegate it because you probably knew that it wouldn't make it faster or better. So I wonder if there's a part of AI that because we talk a lot about like, you know, like.
[Guest] 这对我来说才是关键。关键就在于，现在这个盘子不是在增长，而是在爆炸式扩张。我们内部已经推进了很多项目，而这些项目我们以前甚至连开始都不会考虑。我们的 Legion，
companies love to measure especially larger ones like efficiency PRs and they want to see impact but about the impact of doing work that we would have not done before
[Guest] 我们有个很棒的项目。通常做性能优化时，大家会关注 P50、P95、P99。Jeremy 是我们团队里最会用 agent 提速的人之一，他当时就说，那 P1 呢？下限呢？我们能不能把下限也优化掉？这个下限到底是多少？
That's the kicker for me. That's the fact that the pie is just exploding right now. It's not growing. It's exploding. The number of projects we have tackled internally that we would never even have contemplated starting on. Our Legion,
[Guest] 然后他说，嗯，我们现在的下限我忘了具体是多少了，就假设是 4 毫秒吧。对吧？但其实 4 毫秒也会累积起来，如果你有一大堆很快的请求，它还是有影响的，还是重要。他就直接说，我们要做 P1，我们要优化 P1，字面意义上就是最快的那 1% 请求，我们还要让它们更快。他把这个指标从我记得大概 4 毫秒，降到了不到 0.5 毫秒，性能直接提升了 10 倍。我当时就想，这种项目我绝对不会拍板去做，结果他真做了。
we had a great project where normally on performance work, you worry about P50, P95, P99. Jeremy, one of our most agent accelerated people went like, what about P1? What about the floor? Can we fix the floor? What is the floor?
[Guest] 他把这个 P1 项目当成一个顺手做的 side project，用了几天就搞定了。
and he went like well right now our floor is i forget what it was four milliseconds let's say that right well actually four milliseconds can add up if you have a bunch of fast requests they can still it still matters and he just went like we're gonna do p1 we're gonna optimize p1 literally the fastest one percent of requests we're gonna make him even faster he took it from i think it was four milliseconds to less than half a millisecond he 10x the performance that i was like i would never have signed up on this and he did you
[Guest] 因为现在他做得到。
he did the p1 project over a couple of days as like a side gishef now
[Guest] 他之所以做得到，是因为他有个直觉，觉得这里面有东西可挖，于是他让 agents 放手去跑。最后冒出来一堆 PR，像是，好，这个修一下，那个修一下。我记不太清 P1 项目的具体数字了，我印象里大概有 12 个 PR，就是修了各种各样的问题。单看每一个 PR，我都会想——
Because now he could.
[Guest] 对，确实，行，说得通。我再看改动量，有些你直接改了 2500 行代码，我就会想，你这几天里就把这事做完了？
he could because he had a hunch he had an intuition that there was something here he let agents run with it and the number of prs that like all right we'll fix this we fix this i don't think totally the pr the p1 project i maybe misremembered i think it was like 12 prs like just fixing all sorts of things where i look at the single prs i'm like
[Guest] 所以我以前从没听过有人去做 P1，因为这听起来就像个面子工程，从业务上看完全不合理。当然，这么说也不完全对，因为所有东西都会累积起来。但你明白我的意思吧？
Yeah, actually, okay. Yeah, makes sense. I look at the tone some of it you've changed 2500 lines of code you're like you've done that in a few days
[Host] 我完全懂你的意思，这也正是为什么 pie 的突然爆炸式增长，让我们开始能去看那些以前根本不会考虑的问题。挺有意思的，我记得《Terminator 2》里有个场景，他们找到了从终结者身上拆下来的那块芯片。
And so I've never heard anyone do P1 because it just it feels like a vanity project. It makes no business sense. I mean, this is not true, right? Because everything adds up. But you know what I mean, right?
[Guest] 在第一部电影里，他大概是这么说的：这东西给了我们一些以前根本不会去研究的想法。这里面其实有种很妙的对应——也许我们正要造出《Terminator》那套老生常谈的东西，但与此同时，我们也得到了以前根本不会去想的点子和野心，因为现在验证一个直觉的成本一下子降了一千倍。我现在也老这么干。
i know exactly what you mean and this is exactly why the explosion of the pie suddenly lets us look at problems we would never have contemplated looking before it's funny i remember this scene from terminator 2 where they found this chip from the terminator
[Guest] 我会先随便丢给它一些很模糊、很烂的指令，因为我脑子里只是闪过一个念头，甚至还没整理成一个像样的 prompt，我只是想先看看会出来什么。然后我就会说，哦对，删掉，也就是把代码恢复正常。以前的话，我会更舍不得那 75 行代码，因为那得花我两个小时才能写出来。现在这些东西根本没什么残余价值，我就可以直接说，给我看看一条裙子。
in the first movie and he goes like this thing gave us ideas we would never have investigated before and like there's some beautiful parallels here about like maybe we're about to build the terminator the cliche but also we're getting ideas we're getting ambitions we would never have looked at before because suddenly the cost of exploring a hunch has just dropped by a thousandfold i do this all the time now too
[Guest] 我会有点像个国王一样，张口就来：把那些偏远地区的分析给我呈上来。税收现在什么情况？然后这个小男仆、这个仆人就会说：是，我这就去办，三周后回来复命。
I'll give it some vague crappy instructions just because I have this fleeting idea I haven't even crystallized it into a neat prompt I just want to see something it'll and then I go like oh yeah delete as in revert code back to normal I'd be like before I would be a little more precious about 75 lines of code because it would have taken me two hours to do them now there's no residual value to any of this stuff and I could just go like show me a dress
[Guest] 只不过现在，你随便挥挥手，那些 agents 就会带着答案回来，哪怕是些蠢问题、烂点子。然后突然之间，它又没那么烂了，反而成了个好主意。然后你就会想，哇，我这是拿这个做的——
I feel like a little bit like a king where you just go like, show me the analysis of the far-flung regions. Where are we with the tax? And this boy is like, this servant is like, yes, I shall do so and return in three weeks.
[Guest] 你看，我甚至都还没真正动手去做呢。
Except like you can just wave your hands around and agents just come back with answers to stupid questions, terrible ideas. Then suddenly it wasn't so terrible. It was actually a great idea. Then you go like, wow, I did this with,
[Guest] 还没有，不过 machi 那帮人从一开始就在提的一个需求，就是双启动——能在 Windows 旁边装个 Linux，这样他们还能继续玩所有游戏。而我当时的反应就是，你知道吗，我又不止一台电脑，所以我要玩游戏的话，直接在 PC 上玩就行了，这又不是我的问题。
watch, I haven't even pulled the trigger on it yet.
[Host] 对。
yet but one of the things when the machi people have been asking for since the beginning is dual boot being able to install linux next to the windows installation so that they can still play all their games and i just went like you know what i have more than one computer so when i play play games i could just do it on the pc it's not a me problem
[Guest] 我完全能理解为什么很多人想要这个功能，只是我自己实在没什么动力花四个小时去把这事研究明白。
Yeah.
[Guest] 然后我刚刚不久前突然想到，哦，这正是那种我不用自己搞明白的问题，直接让 agent 去搞明白就行。所以我一开始先让它走一遍制定方案的流程。这算是个挺大的改动，对吧？要是你把别人的启动记录搞坏了，或者把他们的分区给覆盖了，那严重级别可就很高了，这也是我之前不太想碰它的原因之一。其次，这事还有点麻烦：如果你想在 Linux 分区上用 LUKS 加密，但 Linux 分区又没有占满整块硬盘的话。
i totally get why a bunch of people want it i'm not heavily inclined to spend four hours figuring it out
[Guest] 这就有点棘手了，我不想自己承担这个高风险。我就想，这种事太适合 agent 来干了。所以一开始基本上就是让 Opus 和 Codex 来回 ping pong 一个方案：我先问 Opus，给这个事情出个方案。它想了一会儿，然后给了个还不错的方案。接着我把方案丢给 Codex，让它来挑毛病、做评审。然后我让它们来回过了几轮，最后我看着那个方案就觉得——
and i just uh a little while ago went like oh this is exactly the kind of problem like i don't have to figure it out just made the agent figure it out so i kicked off initially the process of just coming up with a plan this is a pretty good big change right like if you fuck up someone's boot records or you overwrite their petition criticality high which was one of the reasons i didn't want to engage with it secondly it's a little finicky if you want uh lux encryption on the linux partition but the linux petition doesn't own the whole drive
[Guest] 对，这方案很好。我们完全应该这么干。我已经等不及把那个任务划掉，然后直接说，嗯，现在 Omachu 支持双系统启动了。不是因为我做的，而是多亏了你那些乐于助人的小 clinkers。
it's a little hairy i didn't want to take on the criticality i'm like this is perfect for the kind of agent stuff so it started off basically just having opus and codex ping pong a plan like i'll just i asked opus first like come up with a plan for this it thinks for a minute and then it's a come up with a good plan and then i kick it over the codex and like critique the plan and then i had him ping pong back and forth a couple times and at the end looking at the plan going
[Host] 这种程度的野心，我到现在都还没真正内化。就连只是这种感觉——嘿，这里有这些……
Yep, that's a good plan. We should totally do that. And I can't wait to take that one off and just go, yeah, now Omachu does dual boot. Not because I did it, but thank your helpful clinkers.
[Host] 一些直觉、一些需求、一些我想做也许以后会做的项目，而你现在居然可以凭着一个念头把它先跑起来，然后自己去吃午饭——这真的是一个新世界。这也是为什么我觉得很多人会想：好吧，模型还会继续进步，但就算我们明天突然撞墙了，《The Bitter Lesson》不再成立了，真的存在上限，比如说 19 万亿 token，它们最多就只能学这么多——当然这根本不是真的，但假如真是这样，而且我们只能停留在现在这些模型上——
That level of ambition is still something I've yet to internalize. Like even just that, that like, hey, here are these.
[Guest] 那我们接下来十年也还是会不断从它们身上榨出更多价值，继续学习怎么使用这些工具。你在老式电脑上其实就能看到这种现象。比如 Commodore 64，81 年发布，到 85 年大概算是它的主要生命周期——我知道后面还生产了一阵子，但后来 Amiga 和别的机器出来了——那时候上面已经有很棒的游戏了。我的确也是因为 Commodore 64、Commodore 和那些东西才对游戏产生兴趣的。但 20 年后他们还能做到的那些事——
hunches or demands projects that i would like to do and maybe someday and you could kick it up on a hunch while you go to lunch that is a new world which is also one of the reasons i think a lot of people are thinking well the model continues to improve but even if we somehow hit a wall tomorrow the bitter lesson is no longer true there's actually a limit it's 19 trillion tokens that's how much they can learn not true at all but if it was and we had to be stuck with these models
[Guest] 那时候有人已经把所有门道都摸透了，把那颗 1 兆赫兹的处理器压榨到了极致——
we would spend the next decade just getting more and more out of them learning how to use these tools you see this actually with vintage computers so the kind of games they were able to make on the commodore 64 when that was released back in 81 to 85 i think was the main run i know they made it a little longer but then the amiga and other machines came out were great games i mean i got interested in games come with the commodore 64 year come through and all that stuff the stuff they were able to do 20 years later
[Host] 哦，就是当他们——
when someone had just noodled all the secrets and tweaked the one megahertz
[Guest] 处理器
Oh, when they're
[Host] 给老平台那部分做游戏，
processor
[Guest] 对，或者
building games for the old part,
[Host] 对。
yes or
[Guest] 技术上会显得厉害得多，因为我们现在对这些东西了解得更多了。我的意思是，这和那个情况一样——你看 PlayStation，首发时出的第一批游戏，和在我们转到 PlayStation 2 之前出的最后一批游戏，看起来简直像是两个世代的产品。其实我们完全也可以继续对这些模型做到这一点，但是——
yeah.
[Host] 但我们享受不到那种特定的乐趣了，因为三个月后就会有一个新模型发布。
so much more technically impressive because we just know so much more about the i mean same thing with that you look at the playstation first games come out on launch last games before we go to playstation 2 they look from they're like from different generations we could totally continue to do that with the models but
[Host] 不过这点很有意思，因为如果顺着这个思路想下去，当然我们知道新的东西还会不断出现，但关键在于，我们会花大量时间去学习、应用它们，去搭建我们的内部系统，去改变我们构建东西的方式，去接新的项目。比如说，如果我们现在是一个现有团队，大家已经能做更多工作、做更有野心的工作了，那你会怎么考虑团队去承担更多工作、上线更多——
We're not going to have that particular enjoyment because there's a new model dropping in three months.
[Host] 更多产品？你会考虑可能扩大团队，还是保持现状？嗯。
but this is interesting because if we just run with this thought like of course we know new new things are going to come but the point is like we will be spending so much time learning applying them building either our internal systems changing how we build things taking on new projects like if we're an existing team now that people can do more work and more ambitious work how are you thinking of the team taking on more work launching more
[Guest] 以我们现在这套配置来看，我最准确的判断是，同样这些人其实能做更多事。
More products are you thinking of of potentially growing the team or keeping it as is Mm
[Host] 嗯。
My best assessment for our setup is that the same people can do much more.
[Guest] 我们先把这一点真正消化掉，但光这一点其实就已经够了。我们本来就已经做得够多了。本来就还有余量，只要我们有足够多的好点子，完全可以再多招很多人。所以。
-hmm
[Guest] 团队现在多出来的这些生产力，让我们能去做像 P1 以及其他这些很棒的项目，而且它们也会更快地改进产品。当然会。以前那种觉得交付一个重要功能要花两个月的想法，
Let's internalize that, but that's also enough. Already we were doing enough. Already we had margin that we could hire way more if we had enough good ideas for that. So.
[Guest] 我是说，那已经彻底过时了。速度肯定会大幅提升。而且这种变化会一路渗透到我们的软件方法论流程里，比如 ShapeUp 就是建立在两个月周期上的。现在那套东西已经完全不再像以前那样说得通了。
All this extra productivity we're getting out of the team allows now to do things like P1 and these other projects that are awesome and they're going to improve the product faster too. Of course they are. The old way of thinking like it's going to take two months to deliver a major feature,
[Guest] 已经不一样了。我们还没有把那些套路彻底改写完，因为这种加速还在飞快发生，而且实际上也没有哪家公司真的把这一整套都重写好了。
I mean that's out the door. Of course there's going to be rapid acceleration. That's going to filter all the way into our software methodology process like ShapeUp was built on two month cycles. That doesn't make sense in the same way at all anymore.
[Host] 当你的发布速度快了这么多，你就需要一种方式来控制哪些内容会上线，并衡量它是否真的有效。这里正好提一下我们的首席赞助商 Statsig，他们为团队提供实验和功能开关。
anymore. We have not fully rewritten those scripts yet because the acceleration is still so fast and no company really has rewritten the script on all that.
[Host] 帮助团队快速发布。Statsig 打造了一个统一平台，同时支持实验和持续发布。
When you're shipping that much faster, you need a way to control what goes live and measure whether it's working. This is a good time to mention our presenting sponsor, Statsig, experimentation feature flags for teams.
[Host] 内置实验意味着，每次发布都会自动变成一次学习机会，配合严谨的统计分析，能清楚告诉你功能到底会怎样影响你的指标。Feature flag 让你可以更有把握地持续发布。
That ship fast. Statsig builds a unified platform that enables both experimentation and continuous shipping.
[Host] 而且因为这一切都在同一个平台里、使用同一套产品数据，你们组织内的各个团队就能更好地协作，做出数据驱动的决策。想了解更多，可以访问 statsig.com/pragmatic。
Built-in experimentation means that every rollout automatically becomes a learning opportunity with proper statistical analysis showing you exactly how features impact your metrics. Feature flags let you ship continuously with confidence.
[Host] 说到这儿，我们回到那个即将冲击开发者的转变。
And because it's all in one platform with the same product data, teams across your organization can collaborate and make data-driven decisions. To learn more, head to statsig.com slash pragmatic.
[Guest] 但我还是觉得，如果软件开发者不认为一场转变正在到来，那就是在自欺欺人。以前他们是产出规模的瓶颈，因此也能拿到流向瓶颈岗位的那种薪资。
With this, let's get back to the shift about to hit developers.
[Guest] 如果这些瓶颈突然开始松动，尤其是如果我们把时间稍微往后拨一点，产品经理实际上已经能够……
But I still think software developers are delusional if they do not think a shift is coming where before they were the constraint on how much could be produced and therefore could command the salaries that flow to the constraints.
[Guest] 能够产出可以直接发布、而且能正常工作的改动，那很多事情都会变。我确实觉得，如果要我下注的话，我们已经见到了程序员的巅峰时期——这里说的是那种受过系统训练的程序员群体，他们要么上过学，要么花了不知道多少小时把这门手艺练得很精。
If suddenly those constraints now loosen, especially if we fast forward a little bit where the product manager is actually able to...
[Guest] 未来我们不再需要同样数量的他们来完成同样规模的工作。没错，Jevons paradox 说的是，当某样东西的价格下降时，你会得到更多它，或者说对它的需求会增加，这确实成立。但这并不意味着程序员这个群体就一定会因此被拯救。因为软件产出肯定会比以往任何时候都更多，这点是确定的。顺便说一句，我觉得 GitHub 最近也挨了不少……
able to produce changes that can be shipped and work things are going to change i do actually think if i was going to bet we've seen peak programmer in terms of the learned guild of programmers who went to either school or spend umpteen hours getting really good at it
[Host] 吐槽，或者说批评，某种程度上也算合理。
we're not going to need the same number of them to do the same amount of work now gervonta's paradox where as the price of something goes down you get more of it or you get more demand for it is true but that doesn't mean that our program is going to get bailed out by it just because more software than ever is going to be produced that's for sure by the way i think github has gotten a lot of
[Guest] 很大程度上都和可靠性有关
slack or flack lately justifiable
[Guest] 所以我看到一张图表，说他们的 uptime 只有 92%，这听起来很夸张。我不太确定那具体是在衡量什么，但我能理解一点。我对此多少有点同情。我也觉得其中确实犯了一些错误，但另一方面，现在正在被生产出来的软件数量简直是在坐火箭。作为一个全球性的文明，我们现在产出的软件比以往任何时候都多，软件、软件。
a lot about reliability
[Guest] 比我们以前任何时候都多。就拿 open claw 本身来说，我记得他说那有 40 万行代码。以前做到这个规模，得花 10 年，还得 2000 个人。
so i saw a chart saying they had a 92 uptime which sounds insane i'm not sure exactly what that was measuring but i feel it i have a little bit of sympathy in that i also think there's some mistakes were made but also that the amount of software that's currently being produced is on a rocket ship we are producing as a civilization globally way more software software
[Host] 嗯，也不是 2000 个，不过对，确实得投入很多人。
than we've ever done before i mean open claw itself i thought um He said it was 400,000 lines of code. That used to take 10 years and 2,000 people to get to that.
[Guest] 我的意思是，得花很长时间，对吧？你看，我记得 Shopify 的那个主要单体应用有 300 万行代码。那是 20 年积累出来的。如果把所有参与过那个项目的程序员都加起来，可能得有 2 万人。
Well, not 2,000, but yes, it took a lot.
[Host] 对。
I mean, a long time, right? You look at, I think, the main monolith at Shopify is 3 million lines of code. That's 20 years. And if you collectively sum up all programs who've worked on that, probably like 20,000 people.
[Guest] 现在巨大的变化正在到来。大量软件正在被生产出来。我能理解为什么那边会有点不堪重负，因为这种推进只会越来越快，对吧？而我们……
Yeah.
[Guest] 而我们其实还什么都没见到呢。如果你看看 AI 的采用情况。
Big shifts are coming right now. Lots of software is being produced. I can see why it's creaking a little bit over there because like the pushes are just going to accelerate, right? And we...
[Guest] Curve 基本上没人用，我们这些在 X 小圈子里的人才会这么用。
And we haven't even seen anything yet. If you look at AI adoption.
[Host] 对。
curves basically no one's using it like we all in our little bubble in x are
[Guest] 对，大家都在说不是那样，其实不是的——世界上大多数公司根本没这么做。话虽如此，我觉得 ChatGPT 很快就到了 8 亿用户，显然是有采用的，但规模远远比不上那些走在最前面的公司在做的事，也比不上它给他们带来的加速效果。所以我确实觉得，对普通程序员来说，
Yeah
[Guest] 觉得黄金时代最好的日子可能已经过去了，这个想法是对的。
like yeah everyone's saying no they're not like most companies in the world are just not doing it not withstanding that like i think uh chat gpt got to 800 million users very quickly obviously there's adoption but nothing on the scale of what the companies that are furthest along are doing and how much they're accelerating with it so i do think it is correct for the average programmer
[Guest] 价格肯定会承压，因为像我们这样的公司，本质上有几乎无限的空间去想新功能、做更多事情，然后我们可以把这些额外的生产力全都投入进去，单纯就是做更多。
To think maybe we've seen the best of the golden days.
[Guest] 但也有很多公司只是需要把某件事做完，如果他们能用十分之一的成本把这件事做成，那其实就是他们的优势，对吧？他们只需要做这件事，范围非常清晰、定义非常明确，它就是个成本中心。
Certainly there will be pressures on price because one thing our companies like ours that have essentially unlimited scope to come up with new features and do more and we can then plow in all that additional productivity into just do more.
[Guest] 凡是软件开发属于成本中心的地方，
There's also a lot of companies who just need to do a thing and if they can do that thing at a tenth of the cost, that's actually their advantage, right? They just need to do this thing, it's very neatly scoped and defined, it's a cost center.
[Guest] 它就会
Anywhere where software development is a cost center,
[Guest] 这个趋势
It's
[Guest] 实际上会真正落地。
which is
[Guest] 可能会影响到全球大多数的软件开发。他们都会面临这些压力。
going actually to hit.
[Host] 对。听起来如果我现在是一名软件工程师，而且我在担心，比如说，我只是想确保自己待的地方未来会变得更好。
probably the majority of software development in the world. They're going to face these pressures.
[Guest] 你要么得去一个能脱离成本中心的地方，要么就得在那里变得非常有价值。
Yeah. Sounds like if I'm a software engineer right now and I'm worried about like, well, you know, I just want to make sure that I'm I'm at a place where things are going to be better.
[Host] 显然，你得提升一下自己的技能。另外我也在想，未来会被招聘的软件工程师画像是不是也会变化，因为如果我回头看，比如从 90 年代开始，
You want to be at a place where you want to either get out of a cost center or become really valuable there,
[Host] 就连电影里你都能看到那种刻板印象。他们就是那种不跟别人说话的书呆子，但他们会写代码，懂汇编。然后到了 2000 年代，招聘还是主要看编程语言。
obviously, you know, brush up your skills. And also, I'm wondering if the shape of software engineers who will be hired will be changing because if I just look back from like the 90s, right,
[Host] 再往后，我觉得到了 2010 年代，创业公司开始不再按语言招人，而是更看重算法能力，因为其他东西是可以学的。现在我看到一些公司，尤其是一些最近拿到 VC 投资的公司，会招 product engineer，他们实际上会要求同理心、沟通能力这类素质，除此之外，默认你本来就会写代码之类的。所以我在想，如果我只是看这条曲线，如果我只是把它大致勾勒出来的话。
like even if you look at the movies, you saw the stereotypes. types they were that the nerds who didn't talk to anyone but they knew how to code they knew how to do assembly and then we went in the 2000s it was still based on languages
[Host] 就像你开始会接触到一些人，哦，还有我在这些公司里见到的开发者，他们人都特别好，都很
and over time i think in the 2010s startups started to not hire for languages but just hire for algorithms because you could learn the stuff and now i'm seeing companies uh some of the the latest vc funded companies hire for product engineers where they they're actually asking for like empathy communication on top of like it's kind of a given that you you know how to code or whatever so i wonder if i'm just looking at just just this curve right if i'm just painting it up
[Host] 善于沟通，非常
Like you're starting to get people oh and the developers that I meet at all these companies. They're all really pleasant they're all
[Guest] 对。
just very communicative very
[Host] 哦，而且他们会和客户交流，大多数人都这样。这甚至不算什么苦差事，反而是，而且越来越多人还很喜欢做这件事
Yes.
[Guest] 这就是现在的瓶颈价值所在。现在的瓶颈在于搞清楚我们该做什么？应该怎么做？该和哪些客户沟通？重点该放在哪里？这其实就是产品管理。对我来说这也很有意思，
oh and they talk with customers most of them just it's it's not even a drag it's like and more and more of them love doing it
[Guest] 因为从历史上看，我不一定一直都很看重产品管理这个职能。我觉得里面有很多扯淡的东西，也觉得有不少人可能并没有做那么多事，对吧？
That's the constraint value now. The constraint value is figuring out what should we build? How should it be built? Which customers should we be talking to? Where should we be focusing? It's product management. It's so funny for me, too,
[Guest] 其中一个原因就是，他们其实做不了，因为真正受限的资源是落地实现。
because historically I've not necessarily had the highest esteem for product management as a function. I thought there was a lot of bullshit and I thought it was a lot of people who maybe didn't do as much, right?
[Guest] 也就是说，产品经理可能已经搞清楚他们想做什么，“我想做这个功能”，然后还得等四周，等一些成本很高的程序员把它真正做出来。在这四周里，我是说，我猜他们也可以去找一些人聊聊——他们其实没有被充分利用，他们不是瓶颈，对吧？真正的瓶颈在实现端。而这一点绝对会发生转变，现在纯粹的实现已经是
And one of the reasons was that they couldn't because the constraint resource was the implementation.
[Guest] 这个问题迟早会被解决的。我不是说现在就已经解决了；如果有人这么说，那他肯定没试过在没有评审的情况下，直接把五份 AI 写出来的代码部署到大型代码库里。不过，吸取了去年夏天在 Lex 上的教训，我也不会把话说死，不会拍着胸脯说这事在明年夏天之前绝对不会发生。
was the product manager could find out that they wanted to do something i want to do this feature and then they had to wait four weeks for some very expensive programmers to make that reality happen and in those four weeks i mean i guess they could go talk to some they were underutilized they were not the constraint right they the constraint was on the implementation that absolutely is going to switch and now pure implementation is
[Guest] 再说一次，这其实就是常识：对于通用场景，某一种实现方式会被解决；但对边缘场景，会花更久；还有一些场景里，这事压根就不合理。就像自动驾驶一样。
going to be solved at some point i'm not claiming it is right now and anyone who is have not tried to just deploy five coded stuff with no review to major code bases but as the lesson of last summer on lex i'm not going to put my hot on the block and saying that's not going to happen before next summer
[Guest] 自动驾驶放在这种尺寸的车上没问题，但像卡车这种，要么需要更长时间，要么如果你是特殊场景……重点是，总会有一些这样的细分区域，不过——
again this is just like common sense but implementation one implementation will be solved for for a general use case for the edge cases it will take longer and for some cases it will not make sense same thing as i know yourself
[Host] 对。
self-driving is fine for like these size of cars but for like trucks it'll either take longer or if you're special but the point is like there will be pockets where but
[Guest] 但这些区域会越来越小。
Yes.
[Guest] 对。我确实觉得，那种“我就只想坐那儿写代码”的刻板印象——你得强到 John Carmack 那个级别，才能保住这种特权，才能说“我就只想坐着写代码”。对。
those pockets will be smaller
[Host] 而且就连 John Carmack，我是说——
Yes. I do think the stereotype of I just want to sit in code. you have to be john karmic levels of good to retain that privilege to just i just want to sit and code yeah
[Guest] 当然，他在 AI 方面也超级强。
and even john carmack i mean
[Host] 嗯
of course he's also super ai
[Host] 有吸引力，而且会主动投入进去
well
[Host] 但同时，他也看出了一些自己可以把握的趋势。比如说，你得知道人们会买什么类型的游戏，对吧？他需要具备一些商业能力，或者身边得有懂这些的人。
appealed and leaning in
[Guest] 完全同意，完全同意，完全同意，但你真的得做到最顶尖，而且——
but also like he he also saw some trends that he could do like for example like just like you know the type of games that people would buy right like he needed to have some business skills or just surrounded by people who did that
[Guest] 不只是最顶尖，你还得比 agents 更强，对吧？你想拥有“只负责执行”的这个特权，前提是你得比现成可用的 agents 做得更好。所以，谁才是真正最顶尖的人？这个问题也很适合问你，因为每次你发布——
totally totally totally but like you need to literally be the very best and
[Host] 一个职位，而且这甚至还是在 AI 之前，我记得你当时招过 software engineer 和 designer。其实我还挺想采访一下你后来招到的那位 designer，因为你会公开薪资，这本身就是个很典型的——
Not just the very best but you need to be better than the agents right for you to get the privilege to just be an implementer You have to be better than what's available off the shelf from from agents So who are the very best and you're a good person to ask because whenever you advertise of
[Host] San Francisco 薪资水平。你会把具体数字直接写出来，大家都能查到。再加上你自己有社交媒体影响力，所以传播得很广，也会收到很多申请。据我了解，你们在招聘上做得相当不错，你会尽量做到非常公平，也投入了很多精力。所以，想被 30 signals 录用到底需要什么？而且现在你们是在努力招最优秀的人。基于这些经验，你会给那些在想“好，我想在当下这个时代成为最优秀的人”的人什么建议？
a position and this was even well before AI I remember that you you put out a job for both software engineer and a designer and actually I want I want to interview your designer who you hired and because you publish the salary which is a sample
[Guest] 这个问题特别好。其实还没有人真正搞明白。我们也还没找到答案。我这么说，是因为作为一个一直——
San Francisco salary you put the exact number you can check it for it you have a social media presence so it kind of goes wide and you get a lot of applications and you do a pretty good job as I understand you try to be very fair you put a lot of effort into it so what did it take to get hired at 30 signals because now you are trying to hire some of the best and based off of this what advice do you give to people who are like okay I want to be the best in in this age right now
[Guest] 经营一家组织时，我们现在肯定已经看过成千上万份候选人资料了。当然，如果你运营的是 Google，那你看过的可能就是几百万了。但我们看过的是几万名候选人，而我们实际招进来的人数其实很少。我的意思是，37 signals 在整个生命周期里待过的程序员总数，大概也就……我不知道，最多 100 到 150 人吧，我甚至都还没
Incredibly good question. No one has figured out. We haven't cracked it. And I say that as someone who have.
[Host] 怎么
run an organization where we we must have looked at tens of thousands of now of course if you're running google you've looked at millions but we've looked at tens of thousands of candidates the number of candidates we've hired is quite small i mean total number of programmers that have been through 37 signals over its entire lifespan was that going to be like i don't know 100 150 at most i haven't even
[Host] 认真算过这笔总账
How
[Host] 你们现在团队大概有多少人？
done the big math
[Guest] 呃，我们整个公司有 60 个人，然后我们有，大概……20 个程序员左右吧，差不多。对。
is your team right now-ish?
[Host] 哦，
uh we're 60 people at the entire company and we are what's that going to be like 20 programmers something like that Yeah,
[Host] 那可能
Oh,
[Host] 确实挺
that's probably
[Host] 差不多。
so
[Host] 另外那 40 个人都是做什么的？
about right.
[Guest] 我们有设计师，
what is the other 40 folks?
[Host] 哇。
We have designers,
[Guest] 大概有 10 个吧。然后我们有客户支持团队，有 14 个人。再就是一些支持职能，像 HR、财务。
Wow.
[Guest] 然后我们还有运营团队，运营这块规模挺大的。我们有 10 个人在管理我们所有的服务器。对，基本上就是这些了。不过是的，我估计大概总共 100 人左右。
probably like 10 of those. And then we have customer support, which is at 14. Then we have a bunch of support functions, HR, finance.
[Host] 对。
and then we have operations operations is quite large we have 10 folks managing all our servers and yeah that's about it but yeah i probably it's probably about 100 people
[Guest] 总的来说，在这家公司里，我合作过或者雇过的程序员，是从我们看过的成千上万份候选人里挑出来的。但即便招进来的这些人，长期来看也不一定都发展得好。其实我最近还看了下，我觉得我们的命中率……
Yep.
[Host] 往好了说也就这样。
in total that i've worked with uh or employed at the company's programmers out of tens of thousands we've looked at and even all those hires did not pan out in the long term like i'd actually say i think i looked at this recently our batting average
[Guest] 我觉得会比五五开稍微好一点。所以有一半的
At best.
[Host] 怎么
I think it's slightly better than 50-50. So half of
[Host] 连那些更高的也……
How
[Host] 你能不能把整个过程讲一遍，因为你们的流程真的又长又细，而且你们确实投入了很多精力，对吧
even those higher...
[Guest] 还没有谁真正搞明白，怎么把招聘做到高效到完全不犯错。Google 很久以前发过一篇很棒的论文，他们测试了各种不同的假设。比如说，我们能不能预测……
can you go through all of because you have a really long and thorough process you you put a lot of effort right
[Guest] 员工的表现，依据是不是 Ivy League 的教育背景、GPA，或者……
No one has figured out just to hire with such efficiency that they don't make mistakes. There's a great paper that Google published quite a long time ago now where they tried all sorts of different hypotheses. Well, can we predict...
[Guest] 这些因素全都试过，结论基本就是：我们其实什么都不知道。靠这些东西根本预测不了。靠 LeetCode 预测不了，靠任何这些指标都预测不了。我要说的是，我显然是因为和一些非常优秀的人共事而被惯坏了，不只是我公司里的人，也包括整个开源社区里的人。
Employee outcomes on the basis of Ivy League education background, on GPA, on...
[Host] 对。哦，对。
all of these things conclusion was basically like we know nothing we can't predict it on any of these things we can't predict it on lead code we can't predict it on any of these metrics now what i'd say is i've clearly been spoiled by working with some very good people not just at my company but in open source in general and
[Guest] 所以这也导致我有时候会对普通程序员的平均水平产生一种有点偏差的看法，
Yeah. Oh, yeah.
[Guest] 他们到底能做到什么程度。每次我们做招聘时，我都会有点——也不是有点，是每一次——都会惊讶于大多数提交上来的东西质量有多差，花在让它看起来体面、像样上的心思有多少。这话听起来很容易显得特别像老派人在抱怨，但这也是找工作的现实：
therefore i've ended up with occasionally a twisted perspective of what the average programmer
[Guest] 你得让自己脱颖而出。我也明白这会让人不舒服，对吧？谁会愿意用一种“嗯，反正胜算本来就不大”的心态来看这件事。但真正掉进陷阱的是，按概率来理解这件事。因为我一再看到有人算错这笔账：他们会说，好吧，有一千个申请者，最后只有一个人拿到工作，或者也许两个人拿到工作，所以我的机会就是 0.1%。不是这样的。
is capable of and when we do hiring rounds i am sometimes well not sometimes every time i'm kind of surprised how poor the majority of the submissions are how little effort is put into being presentable and that can sound really boomer crudgety very quickly but it's also just the reality of trying to get a job like
[Host] 完全不是。按你那个算法，你的机会其实是 0%。
you gotta stand out and i understand that that's uncomfortable right like who wants to look at this as like well the odds are kind of against me but it's also a trap to actually fall into thinking of this in terms of odds because what i've seen the miscalculation happen time and again is people go like okay so you have a thousand applicants there's only one who gets the job or maybe two who gets the job so that 0.1 chance no it's not
[Guest] 对，因为——
Not at all. With that math, you had 0% chance.
[Host] 零。
Yes, because
[Guest] 而且非常
Zero.
[Guest] 最有可能
[Guest] 的那种，
And the very
[Guest] 概率会更高。
the moon's
[Guest] 他们大概有 10% 的机会、20%、30% 的机会。这个分布并不是平均的，也不是抽彩票。我们不是随便抽一个出来，然后说，哦，就这个人吧，因为刚好从这一堆人里抽中了他。
best,
[Guest] 完全不是。我们一开始就会刷掉至少一半的申请，可能是三分之二，只因为他们要么根本没有直接回应这个岗位要求。
got higher.
[Guest] 要么就是没有按照我们那些其实已经说得相当清楚的口头和书面招聘说明来做。对吧。要么明显就不适合这个岗位，或者我们闻到了别的味道。这样大概就只剩下三分之一了。
they probably had a 10% chance, 20%, 30% chance. It is not equal distributed. It is not a lottery. We don't just like pick a thing out and be like, oh, it's going to be this person because they happen to be the one drawn from the bunch.
[Guest] 然后我们就开始看这些提交材料，再一步步缩小范围。按以往经验，最后会筛到大概 20 个人，给他们一个带回家做的测试。这个带回家测试其实很棒。有些人很讨厌，觉得这是白嫖劳动力。我就会想，你他妈在说什么？我难道还会把你代码测试里交的东西直接拿去上线到生产环境吗？你觉得我们那个代码测试是怎么来的？就是因为系统里本来就已经有了。我这话说得可能有点冲，但我也能理解那种心情：如果最后没下文，谁也不想花六个小时去做一个测试。
Not at all. We discard off the bat probably at least half the applications, maybe it's two thirds, just because they're either not addressing the job directly.
[Guest] 好吧，我明白，但这事没有捷径。因为如果你脑子里想的是：你刚投了一份简历，就会有人打电话给你，跟你聊 30 分钟，然后说“先生，你被录用了”，我不知道这种事以前是不是真的存在过，但今天肯定不存在了。至少在我经历过的整个职业生涯里，它从来就没存在过。
They are not following the instructions in the relatively clear spoken written openings that we have. Right. They're obviously not right for it or whatever, or we get some other smells. Then there's like perhaps a third left.
[Host] 嗯，
stuff and then we start looking at some of the submissions then we narrow down historically to a pool of around 20 people that we give a at-home test the at-home test is wonderful some people hate it they feel like it's free labor i'm like what the fuck are you talking about i'm not gonna use your submission to a code test what i'm gonna deploy to production how do you think we came up with that code test because it already exists in the system i say that a little harshly i also get the sympathy of like i don't want to put six hours into making a test if it's not going to go anywhere
[Host] 在这个行业里，
okay i get it but there's no way around it because if you have in your head did you just send in a resume someone's going to call you up on the phone have a 30-minute conversation with you and go you've hired sir i don't know if that ever existed but certainly does not exist today it never existed in the lifetime that i've been in
[Host] 唯一会出现这种情况的时候，对吧，就是通过非常强力的内部推荐，
Well,
[Guest] 没错。
this business
[Host] 也就是说你一开始通常就是
the only time it exists, right, is. through a very warm referral where
[Host] 你是在跳过
Correct.
[Host] 跳过前面的环节。
where you're starting If a typically
[Host] 整个流程。
you're skipping
[Guest] 而当你跳过整套流程时，通常只会发生在公司最早期、也就是创业刚开始的时候。而且往往是双向的，因为风险很高，这时候你会说：我这个哥们儿，我和他一起共事了整整两年，我闭着眼都敢信任他。
tip it
[Host] 这其实就是整个招聘流程最让人幻灭的一面。如果我们看长期成功率的话。
the whole pipeline.
[Guest] 对我们来说，那种“我和这个人共事过两年，我们应该招他”的候选人，最后留下来的长期员工数量，比公开招聘渠道进来的人还多。说实话，要从公开招聘里找到那种能在我们环境里如鱼得水的程序员，真的特别难。确实也发生过，我们也通过这种方式招到过人，而且我还是愿意继续相信这条路，哪怕概率看起来
and when you skip the whole pipe and it's typically only happens at the very beginning of a company when you're founding a company and often it goes both ways where it's very risky and then you say like this buddy of mine i work with this person for two years straight i would like trust them with my eyes closed
[Guest] 低得离谱。你一算就会发现，天啊，我们看了成千上万份，最后有多少被录用，又有多少后来没成，天哪，最后真正留下来的也就那么几个人。从这个角度看，确实挺让人幻灭的。但像你说的那种基于熟人推荐的直接招聘，效果一直非常好，命中率也很高。可这对大多数人有什么帮助呢，对吧？这其实也不算什么特别可执行的建议，除非我们就说，尽你所能把自己变得足够强。
That's actually the black pill on the whole hiring process. If we look at the long-term success rates.
[Guest] 然后尽可能多投入，去和别人一起共事。因为我想顺便反驳一种想法：有些人脑子里会觉得，如果他们在一个自己认为很烂的地方工作，那就没必要认真。
we have had more long-term employees from i've worked with this person for two years we should hire them than we have from the open calls it is actually exceptionally difficult it has been for us to find the kind of programmer who thrives in our environment from open call it has happened we have hired people that way and i continue to want to believe even if the odds seem
[Guest] 兄弟，你这是在坑自己。如果你去一个很烂的工作环境上班，而且我们甚至都可以客观一致地认为那地方就是很烂，然后你就想：那我干脆摸鱼吧，混过去吧，整天刷 Reddit 算了，对吧？但和你一起工作的人都会看在眼里。你知道那种熟人推荐是怎么来的吗？它往往来自某个人曾经在一份烂工作里和另一个人共事，但他注意到那个人
insanely long when you start doing the math of like oh my god we've looked at tens of thousands and how many then got hired and how many then didn't work out like jesus there's only like a handful left from starting that that that's kind of blackmail but then hiring directly on the base of a warm referral as you call it um has worked very well and that the hit rate there's really high but how does that help anyone right like that's not a very actionable advice except let's just say get as good as you can get
[Guest] 依然每天到岗，尽自己最大努力去学习、去交付、去把这些事情做好。这里没有捷径。你就是得真的有本事。而如果你不练习，你就不可能变强。要是你觉得你工作的地方不值得
and put in as much effort as you can and work with someone. Because I want to say that as a counter. Some people have this notion in their head that if they work at a place they consider shitty, they shouldn't try.
[Guest] 配得上你最好的表现，不然你就是在亏待自己。这个说法——
you're shooting your own feet buddy if you show up at the shitty parents of work and we can even be objectively in unison about that that it is a shitty place of work and you then go like well i should just try to skirt i should just try to goof off i should just try to read acts of reddit all day right everyone else you work with they're going to watch that you know what that warm referral is going to come from it's going to come from someone who worked with someone else at a shitty job but identified that that individual
[Guest] 如果你没有在帮忙，哪怕那是个烂地方，如果你没有在帮那个地方变得更好，那为什么一个优秀的地方要雇你？优秀的地方雇人，就是为了把标准继续往上抬。
still showed up and did as best as they could to learn to ship to do all of this stuff there is no shortcut here you simply just have to be good and you will not get good if you do not practice and if you think your place of employment is not
[Guest] 这完全是在自我安慰，而且两边都在自我安慰：一边是“我在一个烂地方上班，所以我才不要投入”。你当然可以不爽，我不是说你非得喜欢你的老板。说实话，我以前共事过的大多数上司，我对他们也没什么特别温暖的感觉，但我还是会非常努力。
worthy of your best you're cheating yourself this
[Guest] 是为了我自己的成长，为了我自己的学习，为了让我自己确信：我是那种会到场、会把事情做好的人。这样当机会来临、当我的全部天赋都被需要、当我的所有技能都打磨成熟时，我就已经准备好了。
If you're not helping, even if it's a shitty place, if you're not helping that place get better, why would a great place hire you who only hires people to further raise the bar?
[Guest] 但是——
is total cope and it's cope both on the side of i work at a shitty place never i don't want to put things in you could be annoyed i'm not telling you you have to love your boss i'd actually say the majority of people i used to work for i didn't have the warmest feelings about them i still tried really hard
[Host] 对。
For my own edification, for my own education, for my own sense of I'm the kind of person who shows up and does a good job so that I will be ready when the opportunity arrives when all my talents are needed and all my skills are honed.
[Host] 你后来进 37 signals，不就是这么发生的吗？当时那好像就只是个合同工之类的岗位，而且你也知道，做合同工你并没有什么归属感，但你还是照样到场，而且——
but
[Guest] 没错。后来 Jason 也意识到了。
Right.
[Guest] 好吧，这个小子最好拿到点股权，不然他现在就得走人。那确实是个很有代表性的故事，但你也不该从那个故事里把所有事情都推演出来。其实说到底，所有创始人的故事在这方面都挺像的，但最根本的原则还是一样：到场，尽你所能把事情做好，在过程中多学东西。还有一种说法，说实话我有点懊恼，某种程度上我可能也推波助澜过一阵子，就是这种观念：
was this not how you ended up at 37 signals where it was just a contract job or something and you know like on a contract job you have no ownership and but you showed up and
[Guest] 你可以是个很厉害的程序员，但其实并不真的喜欢编程；你也完全没必要在工作时间之外还关心编程。
Correct. And Jason ended up realizing.
[Host] 这是你当时的想法吗？
okay this uh punk better get some equity otherwise he's out the door now that's a seminal story and you shouldn't extrapolate everything from that i mean all founder stories by the way are similar stories in that regard but the fundamental principle is still the same show up do as good as you can learn more there also was to my chagrin to some extent i perhaps contributed it to it a bit for a while which was this notion that
[Guest] 嗯，我当时是误以为如此，因为我是在反对那种过度加班、每周干 100 小时、120 小时的疯狂执念。顺便说一句，那从来都不是我的经历。我们创办 Basecamp 时不是那样干的。我们一直都是按每周 40 小时来工作的。
You can be a great programmer and not really like programming, that you don't have to ever care about programming outside working hours.
[Guest] 把这 25 年拉通来看，平均下来就是这样。但同时，就像我一开始说的，我真的很喜欢电脑，所以我在空闲时间也会玩电脑，也会看各种和电脑相关的东西。这不是工作意义上的那种，比如说我一天 24 小时、每周 7 天都在给 Basecamp 客户发功能，那不是这么回事。但我确实会摆弄电脑，会看新东西，会探索新系统之类的。我觉得在 2010 年代有那么一阵子，
Was this what you thought of?
[Guest] 有一种误解，觉得你根本不用做这些事，你只要来上班把活干完就行了。因为编程太有价值了，而真正会的人又太少，所以市场会抢着要你，哪怕是那种根本没多在乎的人他们也照收不误。我觉得这种时代已经结束了——如果它当初真的存在过的话。而我觉得它当时确实存在过。
Well, I thought of it mistakenly because I was pushing back on the overwork, 100-hour week, 120-hour week maniacal obsession, which, by the way, never was my experience. We did not start Basecamp that way. We have worked on a 40-hour week.
[Host] 那些 boot camp 简直就是最完美的——
rolling average over those 25 years but also as i said at the very beginning i really like computers so i play with computers in my free time i look at computer things in my free time it's not work in the sense that i'm whatever shipping features to base camp customers like just 24 7 that's not what it is but i am playing with computers i am looking at new things i am exploring new systems and whatever and i think there was for a while in the 2010s
[Host] 像催化剂一样，或者说它们就像煤矿里的金丝雀，当——
a misconception that you didn't have to do any of those things you could just show up and do your work and you would be so sought after because programming was such a valuable activity and there were so few people who could do it that they'd take anyone even people who barely gave a shit and I think that's over if it ever was true and I think it was true
[Guest] 对。
The boot camps were the perfect.
[Host] 什么？
like catalysts or like they were the canary when
[Guest] 顺便说一句，这本来就是经济应该运作的方式。
Yeah.
[Host] 对。
what
[Guest] 当工资真的很高的时候，就说明劳动力供给不够。所以，我们就应该把更多劳动力补充进来。
Which also, by the way, is how the economy is supposed to function.
[Host] 没错。
Yeah
[Guest] 所以我其实一点都不觉得
When salaries are really high, it means that there's not enough supply of labor. Therefore, we should get labor into the pool.
[Guest] 这有什么问题。
Exactly
[Guest] 我只是说，那种情况已经过去了。
And so I'm not I don't even have any. qualms
[Host] 不，我觉得我们现在讨论的是，程序员的黄金时代是不是已经过去了，我们是不是已经过了“程序员巅峰期”。我在想，所谓程序员巅峰期，可能其实意味着几乎任何想进入这个行业、并且愿意花点力气的人，
about it.
[Host] 花几个月，或者也许几年，都能做到。你可以学会写代码，可以去上大学，也可以去 boot camp，或者自己投入足够多时间，然后就能在某个地方找到工作，因为那时候面试就是那样，也不需要推荐人，我们
I'm just saying like that's over.
[Guest] 对。
No, I think looking we're talking about like is the golden age of the programmer have we passed peak programmer and I wonder if peak programmer really meant that almost anyone who wanted to get into the industry and was willing to put in some effort.
[Host] 当时根本不会查，而这种情况大概正在结束。你确实需要推荐人，而且我觉得会有越来越多公司把背调推荐人作为流程的一部分。而且这不只是走个过场，不是随便问一句“你愿意再和这个人共事吗”就完了。我接过这种电话，像 Databricks 就很有名，他们做推荐人调查时不只是查一下
few months or maybe a few years could do it you could learn how to code you could go to either college or to boot camp or put in the hours and you could get hired at a place because the interviews were their references were not needed we
[Host] 不只是简单核实推荐人，他们会深挖，不光问“你愿不愿意再和这个人共事”，还会问他们有哪些弱点，在哪些方面——
Yes.
[Guest] 对。
didn't check and that is probably coming to an end you do need references you more I think more and more companies will be doing reference checks as part of their thing and that's not just going to be a heavy work there like would you I've had these calls from like Databricks is famous for reference cards they don't only check
[Host] 你会不会雇他们，诸如此类。
really check for references they drill you not just would you work with this person again what were their weaknesses where
[Guest] 现在我明白了。奇怪的是，“巅峰程序员”这个说法听起来像是会影响所有程序员，但其实不是。最优秀的程序员，甚至不是那种全世界就十来个人的“最顶尖”那种，而是真正非常厉害的程序员。
Right.
[Guest] 现在比以往任何时候都更有价值，因为正是他们最能把 AI 带来的加速效应发挥到极致。而真正让我改变看法的关键点是，我也发现——也许这不是放之四海而皆准的——
would you hire them etc etc
[Guest] 但至少在 37 signals 以及我自己的经验里，我现在作为程序员的工作体验，比起 2000 年代初我刚发现 Ruby 那会儿，还要更享受。
Now, I understand it. The weird thing is, peak programmer sounds like this is something that affects all programmers. It does not. The best programmers are not even the best as in like it's 10 people around the world. Really good programmers.
[Guest] 这给我的感觉就像当年我刚发现 Ruby 一样：能在这么多层面上同时推进得这么快，真的特别过瘾。可以去探索那些 P1 项目，可以去思考 Omachi 的 dual booting，还能把所有这些真正能落地的东西都做出来。
are currently more valuable than ever because they're the ones who are able to get the most out of the AI acceleration and this was the kicker for me in changing my perspective on this is that I've also found And maybe it's not universally true,
[Guest] 工作本身已经变得快乐太多了，而且我也在我们那些最积极拥抱 AI 的程序员身上看到了同样的情况。
but certainly within 37 signals in my own experience, I'm enjoying my time as a programmer more than any time since early 2000s when I just discovered Ruby.
[Guest] 也许他们也有一些这样的焦虑，但因为和这些新能力一起工作实在太有意思了，这些焦虑某种程度上就被挤到一边去了。所以这里确实出现了分化，我们都应该感觉到——
This has the I just discovered Ruby feel to it that it is so satisfying to be able to move this fast on so many levels at the same time to be able to explore the P1s, to be able to think about dual booting Omachi, to do all of that stuff that worked.
[Guest] 我们其实并不知道接下来会发生什么，而对有些人来说，这肯定会带来某种程度的焦虑，我能理解。尤其当这关系到你的生计时，你会想：那我七年后还想供得起孩子上大学啊，到时候会是什么样？我懂。但你没法把这种焦虑转化成任何有建设性的东西，除非你把它一股脑投入进去、主动拥抱变化。因为如果你只是坐在那里空转，试图想清楚七年后的世界会是什么样，那就是在浪费时间。所以唯一的路，唯一的路就是——
Work itself has gotten vastly more enjoyable, and I've seen the same thing for the most AI-forward programmers that we have.
[Guest] 我到底能不能对这件事兴奋起来？而我甚至觉得这不需要多大力气。就像我们说的，如果你坐下来和这些模型一起用，把你柜子里吃灰的某个业余项目翻出来——
Maybe they also have some of these anxieties, but they're kind of pushed to the side just out of sheer enjoyment working with the new capacities. So there is a bifurcation here where we should all feel like.
[Host] 那个你一直都没做完的。
well we don't know what's going on and for some people that's going to produce some degree of anxiety i understand that especially when it's your livelihood and you're like well i'd also like to be able to pay for my kids college in seven years what does that look like i get it you're not going to be able to manifest that anxiety into anything productive unless you just plow it into leaning in right because if you just sit and spin around and try to think about what the world's going to look like seven years from now you're wasting your time so that's the only path the only path is
[Guest] 你一直没做完，但你还是去试了一下。我很难理解，一个人如果真的喜欢电脑，怎么会不觉得这种实验很有意思。
Do I ever get excited about this? Which I don't even think takes that much effort. As we said, if you sit down with these models, you pull out one of your hobby projects from the closet that
[Guest] 而且我在很多刚入门的人身上都看到过这种情况。Kent Beck 就是个特别好的例子。他已经写程序 52 年了，他现在还在说自己依然热爱这件事。他找到了一个平衡：一方面用这些 agents 去做一个他一直想做、而且很有野心的东西——他在做一个 Smalltalk server，这东西以前得花特别久，现在离做成越来越近了，虽然还是要花很长时间；另一方面，中间他也会放松一下，他家在湖边，他就出去待着，看看鸟，一看就是两个小时，然后再回来继续。
That you never finished.
[Host] 然后再回来接着干。真美好。
you never finished and you just give it a try. I don't see how you really like computers and not find that experiment. Enjoyable.
[Guest] 顺便说一句，Kent 一直都是我心目中的超级英雄之一。那会儿正是我刚开始学编程的时候，就在我开始接触 Ruby 之前，
and i've seen this with with people who are getting into it kent beck is such a great example he's been programming for 52 years and he is saying like he he loves doing it and he found this balance between using the agents to build something ambitious that he always wanted to build he's building a small talk server which which used to take forever and now it's getting closer and it's still taking a long time and then in between he's chilling at his he has his house on on the lake and he just goes and like just looks at the birds for two hours and then gets back
[Guest] 我在 2001 年丹麦的一个大会上看过 Kent 上台演讲，我完全被他迷住了——不管是他对内容的掌控力，还是他的大胆，还有他那种……
It's back to it. It's beautiful.
[Guest] 他演讲有多出色。那还是在我已经读过《Extreme Programming》和很多其他东西之后。《Smalltalk Best Practices》是我给任何程序员的头号推荐，如果你想学那种最细枝末节的东西，比如一个方法、一个类到底该怎么组织，诸如此类。《Smalltalk Best Practices》是 Kent 的书，我记得是 95 年还是 96 年出的，直到今天它依然是我最喜欢的一本关于战术层面编程模式的书。
Kent is, by the way, one of my all time heroes. This was right when I got started in programming, right when I before I was picking up Ruby,
[Guest] 呃，所以听到他一边玩 agent pilot，一边还能享受看鸟，真的很棒。我的意思是，我自己也在努力这么做。不过这里面现在其实有一点张力：我发现大多数全力投入的人，工作都比他们以往任何时候都更拼。我自己现在也是这样。当你能够这么……
I saw Kent speak at a Danish conference in 2001 on stage and I was completely mesmerized by his command of both the material, how bold he was and how.
[Guest] 在花一个小时监督这些 agent 时，那种高效又有产出的感觉，真的很让人上头。如果你脑子里本来就有那种“东西一发布就会被触发”的多巴胺回路，那简直就是……
great of a speaker he was and this was after having read extreme programming and many of these other things small talk best practices is my number one recommendation for any programmer who want to learn the nitty-gritty of how to structure a method and a class and the rest of it small talk best practices which is kent's book from 95 i think or 96 is to this day my favorite book of all time on tactical programming
[Guest] 会变得超级活跃，对吧。是啊。现在我得提醒自己，你知道吗，这又不是什么限时抢购；AI 下个月还会在，之后几个月也还会在。我不能把自己搞得像在面对限时促销一样，觉得必须在接下来两周内把所有多巴胺都榨干。说真的，我觉得这恰恰是现在那些走得最前、最被它彻底洗脑的人面临的主要挑战：要记住，这东西——
uh patterns so it's wonderful to hear him being agent pilt while also enjoying the birds i mean i try to do that too and this is actually there's a bit of attention right now is that most of the people i find who are all in they're working harder than they ever have and i've seen that with myself now too when you can be this
[Guest] 就像那句老话说的，它们现在已经是它们这辈子最差的时候了，对吧。那你可一定得想办法，别让自己被它彻底吞没，哪怕它确实很让人兴奋。
effective and impactful on an hour of supervision of these agents is really intoxicating. If you have an active dopamine loop up there that gets triggered when something is shipped, it is just...
[Host] 对，对，而且这种“被吞没”的感觉确实很严重。就像 Steve Yaggy，他看起来明显更疲惫了，视频里都能看出来。但他也很坦诚，他确实正在被这股东西卷进去，他自己在做，他身边也有朋友在做。你现在也处在那个前沿位置，很明显你已经被 AI 洗脑了，但你是怎么努力保持平衡的，比如——
hyperactive right Yeah. now and i need to go do you know what this is not like a limited sale like ai is going to be here next month and the months after that like i cannot just operate as though it is a limited sale and i need to get all the dopamine harvested within the next two weeks that i actually think is the main challenge right now for the people who are furthest along and most pilled on it is like remember that this is
[Host] 比如说抽离一下，你懂的。像我知道你之前好像提过睡眠的重要性，而且听说你都不用闹钟。
as bad as they're ever going to be as the cliche goes right you damn well better find a way not to get consumed entirely about it as exciting as it is
[Guest] 没错。我不用闹钟，不过我太太现在会用，因为孩子们得按时去上学。但对我来说，每晚睡满八小时，是你能为自己的认知能力做的最好投资。
and and yeah there's this consuming is is a big deal like it was steve yaggy he was he looks a bit more drained than like you can see it on the video but he he is he's honest like he's he's being pulled into this he's doing he has friends who are and when you're on the edge you're there you've clearly been ai pilled but how are you fighting of keeping a balance of like
[Guest] 所以每一次只要我没睡到八小时，我都会再次意识到，这笔交换实在太不划算了。如果你从八小时降到六小时——
like stepping away you know like i know you've i think you previously talked about the importance of sleep apparently you don't have an alarm
[Guest] 我就会想，好，那样的话我会清醒着过 18 个小时，为了少睡一两个小时、多醒着那一点时间，我接下来这 18 个小时到底要背负多大的状态损耗？这笔账实在太烂了，根本算不过来。当然，偶尔也不是我能控制的。其实尤其是最近这波 AI 的事，我确实有过几次失眠，很少，十根手指都数得过来，那种睡不着的时候就像——
Correct. I don't use an alarm, although my wife now does because the kids need to go to school on a regular basis. But yeah, for me, eight hours a night is the best investment you can make in your own cognitive capacity.
[Host] 脑子会稍微转得快一点
So I just am reminded every single time I do not get eight hours that it is such a poor trade. If you go from the eight to the six.
[Guest] 对。
i go like well i'm going to be awake for in that case 18 hours what is the drag i'm going to carry for all those 18 hours for getting one more hour two more hours by cutting back on the sleep it is such a bad piece of math it makes no sense now occasionally it's involuntary i have actually had especially around this ai stuff i've had a couple of times very rare i can count on two hands the number of times where i've been sleepless like the
[Guest] 这种情况对我来说不算常见，现在也还是不常见，不过我确实经历过几次，所以我能理解那种兴奋感是从哪来的。但我也想说，你最不该拿去交换的就是睡眠，其次也不该牺牲健康。你不该为了多做点 agent 相关的工作，就省下每周三小时锻炼时间，这笔账特别不划算。一定要把身体状态保持好，如果你想让上面那个脑子一直保持敏锐，没有什么比这更重要了。
the brain racing a little
[Guest] 也就是说，身体系统的其他部分也得正常运转，就算达不到最佳状态，至少也要维持在一个良好、可持续的水平，对吧。我确实觉得现在有些人已经快把自己折腾垮了。
Right.
[Host] 对。
too much that's not typical for me and it's still not typical but i have had a couple of them right so i get where some of that excitement comes from but i'd also say the last thing you should trade is sleep and then you should not trade your health you should not try to save the three hours a week of working out to do more agent work that's a very poor trade keep in good condition like there's nothing this can be more important if you want to keep like sharp up there
[Guest] 有些
that like the rest of the system is operating if not at peak capacities then at uh at a good sustainable level right and i do think there are some individuals right now who are at fear of running ragged on
[Guest] 事情是我们接下来很长一段时间都要面对的，所以放慢点，朋友。就算不是接下来十年，至少也是未来几年，我们会看到越来越多，这只会变得越来越疯狂。所以别透支你的健康，别透支你的睡眠，也别糟蹋你的饮食去换任何东西，因为哪怕只看短期，这也根本行不通。你不可能靠
Yeah.
[Guest] 比如说连续三周每晚少睡两三个小时，就让自己变得更高效。三周之后你脑子里根本不可能还剩下什么清晰的东西，你整个人都会乱成一团。
some
[Host] 那我们就收个尾吧。我们聊了很多其实并不了解的东西，还有很多我们不知道的事，但最后想聊聊你真正知道的东西。
thing that we're going to be dealing with for like slow down buddy like if not again limited sale the next 10 years we're going to see more and more it's going to get crazier and crazier so don't squander your health don't squander your sleep don't squander your diet in the service of anything because even on the short term it does not work you cannot get more productive within
[Host] 你其实很久以前就可以退休了，轻轻松松过日子，听听鸟叫之类的。到底是什么让你一直做下去、一直创造、每天都还愿意起床？在 AI 之前，你会打开 terminal，我记得你好像分享过，你会去折腾那些东西；而现在你在和 agents 打交道。到底是什么在驱动你？再往前看，有哪些事情是让你感到兴奋的？
Three weeks, let's say, by trying to cut back two or three hours of sleep every night and then think there's anything coherent left after three weeks, you will be a hot mess.
[Guest] 驱动我的，始终是我对计算机发自内心的热爱。对我来说，这就是度过时间最好的方式，也是最有趣的方式。我当然可以把时间花在很多事情上，我也确实会花时间做很多事。我不只是玩计算机，我还开赛车。
So let's close we talk about the stuff that we don't know a lot of things we don't know but let's close with what
[Guest] 我也会给自己放很多假。我有三个孩子，我们也很享受这些生活里的事。但如果我每天要拿出八个小时来做一件事，那最适合我的还是计算机。从我真的只有五岁的时候起，就一直是这样。
you do know so you you could have retired a long time ago and just you know kick back and and like listen to birds what is it that keeps you doing keeps you building keeping getting up every day and before ai you would open your terminal i think you you shared like like you would go and then and right now you're dealing with agents like what drives you and and and looking ahead like what what are things you're excited about you
[Guest] 不管是打电子游戏，还是现在这种其实有点像电子游戏的感觉——给这些 agents 做监控和埋点，像玩一点 Starcraft 那样调动它们、指挥它们。
My drive continues to be a deep love of computers. This is simply the best way, the most fun way to spend my time. I could spend my time on a lot of things. I do spend my time on a lot of things. I don't just do computers. I drive race cars.
[Host] 谢谢你，Oreo。
I take lots of time off. I have three kids. We enjoy all of that stuff. But if I'm going to fill eight hours every day with an activity, my best bet is computers. And it has been so since I was literally five years old.
[Guest] 对，没错。所以我就是单纯很喜欢计算机。无论我是不是出于经济上的原因需要这么做，我都会继续摆弄计算机，
Whether it's video games or what now feels a little bit like a video game, actually, instrumenting all these agents and playing a little bit of Starcraft with moving them around.
[Guest] 看看它们到底是怎么运转的，然后做出东西来。我觉得大家对财富还有一个很大的误解，就是他们会把它想成某种检查点。
Thanks Oreo
[Guest] 好像一旦你成功了，就可以往后一躺、悠闲度日，仿佛那就是幸福。可过去一百年的心理学研究早就告诉我们：不是，那其实是痛苦。如果你拥有大把时间，却没有目标、没有使命，光靠休闲是远远不够的，也不会让你有满足感。这一点从例子上看其实再明显不过了。
Yes, exactly. So I just really like computers. So whether I need to do so for economic reasons or not, I will continue to play with computers,
[Guest] 几乎每个把公司卖掉的创业者都是这样：在海滩上坐三周，然后又重新回到牌局里了，对吧？因为
see what makes them tick and make things. I think that's the other big misconception that some people have about wealth is that they conceive of it as some sort of checkpoint.
[Host] 对。
point like once you've made it then you can just kick back in leisure as though that was happiness we simply have a hundred years of psychological studies telling us no that's misery if you have all the time in the world and no purpose no mission leisure is not going to cut it it's not going to be fulfilling way and this should be obvious by example
[Guest] 这其实不只是他们为了某个目标去做的事，这件事本身就是目标本身，就是使命本身。
of literally every entrepreneur who sells their business they sit on the beach for three weeks and then they're back into the game right because
[Guest] 这本身就是满足感。这是在确认自己作为一个人而存在的价值：我不只是一个瘫在那里的一团东西，我是一个有用的人，能把自己的技能发挥到最大价值。
Yeah
[Guest] 所以我会继续做下去。而且不管我是坐在那里敲键盘，
this is actually not just something they do in pursuit of a goal it's the goal itself It is the mission itself.
[Guest] 还是在给这些 agents 做部署和调试，还是它们在教我，不管具体是哪种方式，我都想和电脑打交道。我会继续做下去。然后——
It is the satisfaction. It is the affirmation of being a human that I'm not just a blob laying around. I am a useful individual who put my skills to the best use possible.
[Guest] 更具体一点，尤其是过去这三个月之后，我现在正在全力投入 agent accessibility 这件事。
So I'm going to continue to do that. And I'm going to continue to do it whether I'm sitting tapping at the keyboard,
[Guest] 比如说，这就是我过去几周一直在做的事。我们一直在做新的 CLI，这也让我意识到，我们离 AGI 其实还没那么近，对吧？你会觉得，嗯，直接让 agent 去做个 CLI 不就行了。它是能做，但还没完全到位。
whether I'm instrumenting these agents, whether they're teaching me, however which way it is, I want to play with computers. I'm going to continue to do that. And then.
[Guest] 对吧？我希望它能做到恰到好处，而这些 agent 现在还是需要一点帮助。我也很乐意给它们提供这种帮助，我们很快就会为 Basecamp 发布一个非常非常棒的 CLI，大概吧。
And then even more specifically, after the last three months, I'm leaning in hard now with agent accessibility,
[Guest] 也许等这期播客上线的时候，它可能已经发布了，其他那些东西也是。我想更深入地拥抱这一切——我们怎么才能尽可能多地用上这些东西。然后现在，我也真的就是一个好奇心特别强的人，我每天早上醒来
for example. This is what I've been doing last few weeks. We've been working on the new CLI, which also taught me like we're not quite at AGI yet, right? You think like, well, just ask the agent to make a CLI. It will, but like it's not quite there,
[Guest] 我现在有了一个新仪式，就是不要一醒来就拿起手机开始刷 X。我其实不觉得那样有多好，但要忍住不这么做，真的需要非常强的意志力，因为我实在太好奇到底发生了什么。
right? Like I want it to be just right and the agents still need a little bit of help. I'm very happy to provide that help to these agents and we'll release a great CLI for Basecamp very, very shortly, maybe.
[Guest] 现在发生的事情太多了。我想知道，我想知道。我想享受这一切，也想参与其中。所以我不觉得这种状态会结束。我也不觉得自己对电脑的热爱会消退。恰恰相反，如果非要说的话，
maybe by the time this is out it'll probably be out and for the rest of them too and i want to lean into all this how can we use this as much as we possibly can and then right now i'm also just an incredibly curious person i wake up every morning
[Guest] 我现在看到的反而是一种蓬勃发展。我比五年前更喜欢电脑了。这太棒了。
I have a new ritual, which is not to pull my phone up and start hopping on X. Right when I wake up, I don't think actually that is great, but it takes a tremendous willpower to not do so because I'm just so curious about what happened.
[Host] 太棒了！David，这段聊得真精彩。非常感谢！
There's so much happening right now. I want to know. I want to know. I want to be enjoying it, be a part of it. So I don't foresee that ending. I don't foresee a love of computers evaporating. In fact, if anything,
[Guest] 好的，感谢邀请我来。这次聊得真的很棒。
right now I'm seeing like a flourishing of it. I'm liking computers more than I did five years ago. And that's amazing.
[Host] 这次对话非常精彩，我也很喜欢 David 身上的那股劲儿。我希望这种当面就能明显感受到的能量，你也多少感受到了。
Amazing! David, this was awesome. Thanks a bunch!
[Host] 我也很欣赏 David 很坦率地说，他对 AI 的立场并不是因为自己的理念变了，而只是因为这些工具终于好到足以做出真正有用的东西。以前那种拿 AI 做自动补全，对有经验的开发者来说其实挺烦人的。
All right, thanks for having me. This is really great.
[Host] 但现在，AI agent 已经能自己产出相当不错、能跑起来的代码了。
This was a fascinating conversation, and I loved the energy that David has. I hope some of this energy that is obvious in person also came across to you.
[Host] 另一方面，这些东西现在确实已经很有用了。可即便如此，David 还是反复强调品味、判断力和手艺。他并不是在说随便让模型爱写什么写什么，恰恰相反。
I really appreciated that David was open that his stance did not change about AI because his philosophy changed. It's just that the tools became good enough to do useful stuff. AI for autocomplete was annoying for experienced developers.
[Host] 他的质量标准非常高，他希望产出的代码是那种自己真的会很自豪地合并进去的代码。这让人感觉，AI 也许会让好的判断力变得比以往任何时候都更有价值。
AI agent that can produce pretty good working code by themselves.
[Host] 我也很喜欢 David 对设计重要性的看法。在 37signals，设计师会参与判断到底该做什么、应该怎么运作，而且越来越多时候，连具体该怎么实现都是他们来决定。
Stocks, on the other hand, are now pretty useful. And yet David kept coming back to taste, judgment and craft. He wasn't just saying just let the model write whatever, it's the opposite.
[Host] 我在想，37signals 会不会在这个问题上比整个行业都更超前一步：他们会把设计师也看得有点像开发者，同时也把开发者看得有点像设计师。最后，
He has a very high quality bar and he wants the output to be code that he would actually be proud to merge. It feels like AI might make good judgment even more valuable than ever.
[Host] 我觉得 David 提出的那个观点很有意思：我们也许已经到了软件工程师数量的峰值。David 认为，未来我们产出的软件会比以往任何时候都更多。
before. I also really liked how David thinks about the importance of design. At 37signals, designers help figure out what should be built, how it should work, and increasingly even decide how it gets implemented.
[Host] 但他的观察是，我们可能正在接近这样一个时代的尾声：开发者仅仅因为自己是瓶颈，就能拿到高薪。我的一点看法是，市场肯定仍然会非常需要那些能打造出盈利软件的专业人士。
I wonder if 37signals is a step ahead of the industry in thinking about designers a bit like developers as well, and developers a bit like designers as well. Finally,
[Host] 但这意味着，软件工程师不能只是擅长写代码，或者会用 AI 生成代码，还得能统筹构建复杂系统，同时具备审美判断和商业 sense。
I found David's take that we might have hit peak software engineer an interesting argument. David thinks we'll produce more software than ever,
[Host] 如果你想听 David 分享更多内容，可以去看看节目备注里链接的那期他的加更节目。也欢迎查看节目备注，里面还有和 pragmatic under deep dives 相关的内容，聊软件工艺以及构建软件的实用方法。
but his observation is that we might be nearing the end of the time when developers could command high compensation simply because they were the bottleneck. My two cents is that there will surely be high demand for professional
[Host] 如果你喜欢这档播客，请在你常用的播客平台和 YouTube 上订阅。要是你还能顺手给节目打个分，那就更感谢了。谢谢，我们下期见。
professionals who can build profitable software. But this will mean software engineers who are not only good at coding or using AI to generate code, but can oversee building complex systems, have taste and business sense as well.